<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A triumph of truth. Or Declaration of the doctrine concerning euangelicall counsayles; lately deliuered in Oxford by Humfrey Leech M. of Arts, &amp; minister. With relation of sondry occurrents, and particularly of D. King, the Vicechancellour, his exorbitant proceedings against the sayd H.L. vpon his constant propugnation thereof. Also the peculiar motiues, ensuing therevpon, which perswaded him to renounce the faction of hereticall congregations, &amp; and to embrace the vnity of the Catholique Church</title>
            <author>Leech, Humphrey, 1571-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14421</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843931</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177048</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240926153</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 15363</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S108259</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843931e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 769:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A triumph of truth. Or Declaration of the doctrine concerning euangelicall counsayles; lately deliuered in Oxford by Humfrey Leech M. of Arts, &amp; minister. With relation of sondry occurrents, and particularly of D. King, the Vicechancellour, his exorbitant proceedings against the sayd H.L. vpon his constant propugnation thereof. Also the peculiar motiues, ensuing therevpon, which perswaded him to renounce the faction of hereticall congregations, &amp; and to embrace the vnity of the Catholique Church</title>
                  <author>Leech, Humphrey, 1571-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Kellam],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Douai :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.IX. [1609]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">King, John, 1559?-1621.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Evangelical counsels --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:2"/>
            <p>A TRIVMPH OF TRVTH.</p>
            <p>OR Declaration of the doctrine concerning EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES; lately deliuered in OXFORD by HVMFREY LEECH M. of Arts, &amp; Minister.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>Relation of sondry occurrents, and particularly of</hi> D. KING, <hi>the Vicechancellour, his exorbitant proceedings against the sayd H. L. vpon his constant propugnation thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO The peculiar MOTIVES, ensuing therevpon, which perswaded him to renounce the faction of hereticall Congregations, &amp; to embrace the vnity of the CATHOLIQVE Church.</p>
            <q>Great is the <hi>TRVTH,</hi> and prevayleth. <bibl>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Esdr. <hi>4.41.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>M.D.C.IX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:3"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED, WISE, AND INGENIOVS ACADEMICKS FLOVRISHING IN THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOWNED VNIVERSITY OF OXFORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>XPERIENCE doth wel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue S. <hi>Bernards</hi> saying; <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacior lingua, quàm litera:</hi> the tongue is of greater efficacie, then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pen. And therfore I suffer no little disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, in that I must now speake vnto you in a silent letter, and plead my cause by a mute aduocate of my minde.</p>
            <p>But since I vvrite vnto them, vvho are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot strangers in my busines, but aswell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye vvitnesses of the vvronges, vvhich I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue endured, as eare vvitnesses of the Doctrine, vvhich I preached amongst <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou; my vndoubted hope is, that your
<pb facs="tcp:177048:4"/> heartes wil be touched with some com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion either tovvards me, vnvvorthily intreated by a faction (for I will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the crime of a fevv vnto all) or tovvards your selues, vvhom this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular doth very highly import, in respect of your learning, honour, and estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For as the iniurie, which God, and his truth haue sustayned in my person, is now made knowne not only vnto our nation, but the fame thereof beginneth to spread it self abroad in theis forayne parts, so it concerneth you (my louing Fathers, and Brethren) to vvype avvay that disgrace, and blemish from your Mother, and your selues, vvhich some of her vnnaturall Children vvould both stayne her vvith, and deriue vpon you; endeuouring to obscure their priuate folly in the publick shame. VVhich pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection I vvil neuer afford vnto them, vnlesse they can obtayn it by your ovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne consent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:4"/>
            <p>VVherefore, out of my affectionate zeale vnto your credit, I do both hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly desire, and earnestly require you to auert this infamy from your noble Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to free hir from the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvhich, othervvayes, you dravv vpon hir, as being eyther a patronesse of falsehood, or fearfull to defend the truth: vvhich folly in the first, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sillanimity in the second, is a great stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto men of your quality, and place.</p>
            <p>For you stile your Vniuersitie the <hi>Fountayn,</hi> and the <hi>Eye</hi> of the kingdome. And you say not vnfitly; forasmuch as the Doctrine there taught doth streame forth into all parts of our nation: and all men come vnto you to receiue informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their vnderstandings, by your Academicall instruction.</p>
            <p>In vvhich respect you stand deepely obliged vnto God, and men (as you haue care of his glorie, and their benefitt) to vindicate the truth from oppression, &amp; to redeeme hir out of captiuitie into
<pb facs="tcp:177048:5"/> freedome, that hir lustre may not be darkened, vvhere so great a pretense is made of the ghospells light.</p>
            <p>Which iust kindnesse if I may not procure at your hands, yet the truth shall not be impayred thereby: nor vvill I be any vvhitt discōfited, othervvayes then in a sorrowfull commiseration of your estate. For my resolution is firmely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vvithin mine ovvne heart, to spare no travayle, that I may purchase condigne approbation of my cause from all the Vniuersities in <hi>Europe:</hi> if iustice may not be there done, vvhere Gods truth, and I (meerely for hir sake) haue receiued such iniurie, as seemeth almost incredible vnto strangers, vvho do not yet suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlie vnderstād the courses of <hi>D. King,</hi> and of other <hi>Caluinists;</hi> the assistents of his spleneticall proceedings.</p>
            <p>Finally (my Brethren) vvith my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest petition, and necessarie counsaill, I ioyne my hearty praiers (and teares vvith them) that it vvould please the authour
<pb facs="tcp:177048:5"/> of all goodnesse, and the God of all truth, to povvre the abundant riches of his grace into your soules, that your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings may be fully enlightened vvith his truth, and that your vvills may be made cōformable therevnto in your profession of the holy Catholicke faith. For vvhich as I novv suffer the vvant of my natiue cōtrey, so, in defence thereof, I shall be ready to yeald vp my life, vvhē it shall please my gratious Lord to call me vnto that honour: vvhereof I am vnvvorthy.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FARE YOV WELL.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Arras.</hi>
                  <date>14. <hi>March.</hi> 1609.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your deuoted Brother in Christ. Humfrey Leech.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:6"/>
            <head>The Generall Contents of this Treatise distributed into three parts.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST PART CONTAYNETH the Authours entrance into the Doctrine of <hi>EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES,</hi> vvith his defence of the same against the secrete murmuration of the <hi>Brethren</hi> in <hi>OXFORD;</hi> and against a certayn lecture read there pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, and purposely in impugnation thereof.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>CHAP. 1. The first ingresse into the doctrine of EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 2. The Vice chancellours silence; the <hi>Brethrens</hi> murmuration.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 3. The sayd doctrine illustrated vpon occasion of the <hi>Brethrens</hi> calumniations.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 4. The Kitchin-conference of D. <hi>Hutton</hi> with the Authour, vpon the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd illustration of this doctrine.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 5. D. <hi>Hutton</hi> required a copy of the former Sermon. His surcease therevpon, as also vpon conference with a learned Doctour, from prosecuting the Authour
<pb facs="tcp:177048:6"/> any farther.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 6. D. <hi>Benefield</hi> his publicke lecture against this doctrine.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 7. The Authours defence thereof, and of the FATHERS in a Sermon.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 8. A conclusion of the first Part, with an admonition vnto the Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Reader.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART CONTAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the irregular, and violent proceedings of the <hi>Vicechancellour,</hi> and his complices against the Authour, and his doctrine. VVhereby the nature of heresy, and hereticks doth plainely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer it selfe.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>CHAP. 1. The Authour conuented by <hi>D. Hutton,</hi> vpon deliuery of the last Sermon.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 2. The Authour indignely vsed by <hi>D. King,</hi> after his returne from <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>CHAP. 3. The finall proceedings of <hi>D. King,</hi> and his assistents against the Authour, and his doctrine.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 4. <hi>D. Kings</hi> perfidious, and vnjust dealing with the Authour.</item>
                  <item>CHAP. 5. The Authour summoned to <hi>Paules</hi> Crosse, and defeated. <hi>D. Kings</hi> conference with a learned Deuine in <hi>London,</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:177048:7"/>
                     <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>CHAP. 6. The Authours appeale vnto the Archbishoppe; and what intertaynment he found in <hi>Lambeth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>CHAP. 7. The Authour (being retired vnto priuate meditation) sought out by one of the Archbishopps Chaplaynes, and solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to repayr agayne vnto <hi>Lambeth.</hi> His resolution vpon a better course.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD PART CONTAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>12. Motiues</hi> (briefly, and naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of the premises) vvhich persvvaded the Authour to embrace the <hi>Catholicke</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>I. The <hi>Protestants</hi> admitte not a triall of their Religion by the <hi>Fathers;</hi> whatsoeuer they pretend to the contrary.</item>
                  <item>II. The <hi>Protestants</hi> preferre the Cōgregations of <hi>Luth. Calu.</hi> &amp;c. before the ancient <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke</hi> Church.</item>
                  <item>III. The <hi>Protestants</hi> brand <hi>Catholicke</hi> doctrine with the name of <hi>Popery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IIII. The <hi>Protestants</hi> subuert the truest meanes of piety, and deuotion.</item>
                  <item>V. The <hi>Protestants</hi> corrupt the Scripture in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their opinions.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177048:7"/>
                  <item>VI. The <hi>Protestants</hi> are <hi>Iouinianists,</hi> and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VII. The <hi>Protestants</hi> accommodate their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion vnto the State, and present time.</item>
                  <item>VIII. The <hi>Protestants</hi> punish not doctrines meerely in respect of their falsehood, but as they are contrary vnto their profitte, and pleasure.</item>
                  <item>IX. The <hi>Protestants</hi> do vnconscionably impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne the knowen, and manifest truth.</item>
                  <item>X. The <hi>Protestants,</hi> for want of better meanes to conuince the <hi>Catholiques,</hi> propose vnto them questions of capitall danger.</item>
                  <item>XI. The <hi>Protestants</hi> manner of proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Catholiques</hi> is absurd in reason, and vnequall in justice. It prooueth them to be Heretiques.</item>
                  <item>XII. The <hi>Protestants</hi> Superiour Magistrats concurre with their inferiours to oppresse the truth, against all conscience, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In the conclusion of this Treatise, ensue the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles;</hi> vvith an Aduertisement to the Reader.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:8"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE vnto the vvhole discourse.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN</hi> I first set footing into this present businesse, my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose vvas not (no not in my most secret thoughts) to enter into any point of controuersie, or to giue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of offence, or dislike vnto any: only my resolution vvas, plainely, and positiuely (as the course of my studies had euer bent, and caried me) to glaunce at a mayne point of doctrine (it comming but <hi>obiter</hi> in my vvay) directly vvarranted, nay lineally deduced frō the vniforme consent of all ancient times; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed vnto vs by the perpetuall tradition, and practise of the Church.</p>
            <p>But yet since, contrary to my probable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion, certaine priuate spirits (vvhose faith is their ovvne fancy) ytching rather after prophane nouelty, and hereticall innouation,
<pb facs="tcp:177048:8"/> thē abiding the vvholsome doctrine of sacred Antiquity, and the Churches dogmaticall tradition, haue, by all meanes, laboured to impugne my doctrine, and to defame my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: I haue thought my selfe in conscience, and duty (both before God, and man) obliged, asvvell for the generall satisfaction of all, vvhom this present businesse may any vvay concerne, as for my ovvne dischardge in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular (being the party herein especially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teressed) briefly to compile, and publish the vvhole cariadge, and progresse of this matter, in the ensuing treatise; humbly recōmending, and euer submitting my opinion vnto the graue, and infallible iudgmēt of the <hi>Church,</hi> at vvhose feete, and tribunall alone prostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my selfe, J must stand, or fall: as also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring my self, vvith the moderate deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my cause, vnto the syncere iudgement of the discreete, and impartiall Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:9"/>
            <argument>
               <p>THE FIRST PART Contayning my entrance into the do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles</hi> vvith my defence of the same agains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the secret murmuratiō of the <hi>Brethre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>Oxford:</hi> and against a certayn Lecture publickly, and purposely read there in impugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            </argument>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177048:9"/>
            <head>A TRIVMPH OF TRVTH. OR DECLARATION OF THE DOCTRINE CONCERNING EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES;</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The first ingresse into the doctrine of <hi>EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NTREATING of this parcell of holy scripture; <hi>I savv the dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In a Sermon at Christs-Church in Oxford 1607 Apocal. 20.12.</note>
                  <hi>both great, and small, stand before God;</hi> I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished a fourefould acception, or signification of <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>small.</hi> FIRST; great, and small for worldly authority, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral condition. SECONDLY; great, and small in respect of heauenly supereminency of grace, and spirituall infusion. THIRDLY; great and small in lieu of diuersity of rewards, and retribution. FOVRTHLY; great, and small in regard of contrariety, and disparity of workes, and operation.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177048:10"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Moral. li. 26. cap. 24. 25.</note>Hereunto I applied that distinction of S. GREGORY; <hi>Quidam iudicantur, &amp; pereunt: quidam non iudicātur, &amp; pereunt: quidam iudican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; regnant: quidam non iudicantur, &amp; regnant.</hi> That is (as another ancient writer, somewhat varying the wordes, but keeping the sense, doth excellently render it) some are to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and damned; <hi>perishing by iudgment.</hi> Some are iudged, &amp; damned already; <hi>perishing vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudgement.</hi> Some are to be iudged &amp; saued; <hi>saued vvith iudgment.</hi> Some are iudged and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued allready; <hi>saued vvithout iudgment.</hi> And all this diuersity of iudgment ariseth from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety, and disparity of workes, acted, and done here in this life, by <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my text.</p>
               <p>This distinction I breifly dilated vpon, as the straightnesse of time (which now had ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me) would giue me leaue, and cōming to the last member of the distinction, in the very close, and vpshot of the sermon, I concluded, that those, who were to be <hi>saued vvithout iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> are such, as did transcend the precepts of the law by due performance of EVANGE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICALL COVNSAYLES of perfection; endeauouring not only to performe the moral obligatory decalogue, but thirsting after more eminent perfection added, nay voluntarily by power of an arbitrary choyce, offered vnto
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177048:10"/> the lawgiuer more, then the generall precepts of the law necessarily tyed them vnto; deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and consecrating themselues vnto the heauenly profession of spirituall <hi>Pouertie,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical <hi>Chastity,</hi> and humble <hi>Obedience,</hi> renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their owne will, forgoing carnall concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence, forsaking all thinges, yea and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, for Christ, and heauens sake. That is to say; they despise the worlds transitory trashe, and pleasures; and only thirst after spirituall goods, which are the true treasure of heauen.</p>
               <p>This was the summe, and substance deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in my first entrance into this point, M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour KINGE (<hi>vicechancellour</hi> of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity) being then present; and giuing no signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of dislike conceyued by him against the verity of this doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Hovv vpon the vicechancellours silence, the <hi>BRETHREN</hi> murmured secretely against the aforesayd doctrine.</head>
               <p>NOw let the indifferent, and iudicious Reader obserue, whether I may not more then probably conclude, that either the <hi>vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chancellour,</hi> at this time, apprehended it not; or apprehending it, in his owne true iudgment,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177048:11"/> and conscience disgusted it not; or distasting it, yet being not able to conuince, and refell the demonstratiue euidence of it, could haue bene content to winke at it, and giue it his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent cōniuency, so that it might thus haue passed away in silence.</p>
               <p>Was the point erroneous? where then was his iudgment, that should haue descried it, if it deserued his censure? why escaped it then vnrebuked? might this doctrine now passe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and must it afterwards be iudged coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaict? In a word: is the doctrine as it was generally intimated, allowable; and are the particulars therof being now dilated, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, made thereupon intollerable?</p>
               <p>Howbeit certaine of a purer strayne (BRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THREN some men call them; and <hi>Brethren</hi> I confesse them to be; <hi>fratres in malo,</hi> as <hi>Simeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> sometimes were) secretly murmured, and beganne in corners priuately (as Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques vsually haue done) to traduce me, my do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine, and my authour S. GREGORY: ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating that in secrete, which openly the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> durst not yet aduenture substantially to im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugne.</p>
               <p>The report, and rumour wherof (by rela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of some frends) no sooner came vnto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eares, but presently (knowing well the assure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grounds of my doctrine) I addressed my self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177048:11"/> to haue satisfied, &amp; contented any ingenious, and vnpassionate auditour, by a second repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a briefe, punctuall, and perspicuous explanation &amp; confirmation of my aforesayd doctrine: For I was alltogether vnwilling to suffer the least imputation or scandall to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened vpon it, or vpon the Authour (were it but in corners secretly) and farther, though I intended not to runne into a publick opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet now occasion might be ministred vnto me, and others to vindicate a necessary truth from the detraction of calumnious ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Hovv the former doctrine vvas illustrated, vpon the <hi>BRETHRENS</hi> priuate calumniation therof.</head>
               <p>BEING thus occasioned by the secrete, &amp; clancular murmuration of <hi>Brethren</hi> (the fame wherof beganne now to disperse it selfe abroad) to addresse some defence of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer doctrine; I tooke the next opportunity to supply the publique place, and willing rather to giue a little further touch to conuince the sayd <hi>Brethren,</hi> then to dwell, as yet, vpon any mayne, and full discourse (which was not my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177048:12"/> purpose; the point being yet not publickly contradicted) I repeated, and dilated vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> point more at lardge; as it was originally de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duced out of the last branch of S. GREGOR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his distinction; to wit, <hi>quidam non iudicantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; regnant:</hi> to this purport, and effect.</p>
               <p>Of this point (sayd I) I may speake as <hi>S. Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> speaketh to the seauen Churches of <hi>Asia;</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluding euer the burthen of his admonitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with a patheticall <hi>epiphonema</hi> in the reprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion; <hi>Let him that hath an eare to heare, heare vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the spirit saith to the Churches.</hi> And may not apply; <hi>let him that hath not only an eare to heare,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a soule to saue by the eares hearing, heare wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the celestiall oracle, heauenly spirit, and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholique Church ioyntly speake, and deliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> concerning EVANGELICALL COVNSAILE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Or I may speake with our blessed Sauiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aduising, exhorting, counsayling, yea, out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the whole masse of mankind, inuiting, nay i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> citing some to that angelicall gift of virgina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chastity;<note place="margin">Math. 19.12.</note>
                  <hi>qui potest capere, capiat;</hi> he that can a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pire to the toppe of angelicall integrity, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him become a votary of virginall Chastity.</p>
               <p>This is <hi>S. Paul</hi> his <hi>sapientia inter perfectos;</hi> ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stolicall wisedome for men of angelicall pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection. These easily disclose, and discouer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worlds foolishenes &amp; impostures, when the paragon them with heauens remuneratiō, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177048:12"/> treasures. These are <hi>the salt of the earth,</hi> and <hi>the light of the vvorld:</hi> starres fixed in the spheare of heauen, the Church militant; not wandring in their motion towards heauen, the Church triumphant.</p>
               <p>These are our best pilotts amongst men; their godly conuersation ought to be our holy imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. These guide by their examples the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of our bodies (wherin the eternall treasures of our soules are caried, <hi>as in earthen vessells</hi>) through the perilous rockes of the seas of this worlde, that they may ariue safely at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed hauen of heauen, when they flitt from the bedd of this mortall body.</p>
               <p>These are beacons on a hill (the hill of the Church) whose liues as lightes, and burning lamps, forewarne, and so forearme vs against all inuasion of any spirituall enimies. These are <hi>entia trascendentia</hi> men foaring aboue the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary pitch of men, celestial men, terrestial An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, surmounting and transcending the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the law by <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles</hi> of perfection: endeuouring not only to performe the law, but thirsting after a more holy, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, and excelling perfection, haue pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more then the lawes generall precepts obliged them vnto; adding ouer, &amp; aboue the law, that which the law wanted of the merit of perfection; as S. BASILL speaketh; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177048:13"/>
                  <hi>spirituall pouerty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De vera vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe finem.</note>
                  <hi>angelicall Chastity,</hi> and <hi>humble obedience;</hi> and all this for heauens sake.</p>
               <p>And that they may more readily follow, and deuoutly adhere vnto Christ they cast away that which <hi>presseth dovvne so fast,</hi> nay which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times presseth downe to hell; ouerloading, and surcharging the soule with immoderate weight; the thorny cares, and choking ryches of this present worlde.</p>
               <p>These with feare and trembling recompt, &amp; remember that terrible interrogation of out Sauiour concerning the worlds riches, &amp; the profit redounding vnto man in the vayne, and maine pursuite therof; <hi>vvhat shal it aduantage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man to winne the vvhole vvorld, &amp; to loose his owne soule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therfore these professors of <hi>Euangelical Counsayles,</hi> merchandising for their soules ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly with al spiritual endeuour vpon the seas of this world, follow the counsayle, which Christ gaue to the yong man (who came to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the WAY to learne the way to heauen) <hi>if tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vvilt be perfit, go sell all that thou hast, and giue t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the poore, and thou shalt haue treasure in heauen, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> come and folovv me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O what an exchāge had this yoūg man made what an offer did Christ make him, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Counsaile did the wisdome of the father giue him, how much doth it now repent him? In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177048:13"/> word: ô how happy had he bene, both in body and in soule, since he had bene secure of the saluation both of body, and of soule, and not only secure of that, but <hi>thesaurum habuisset in coelo,</hi> his pennie had bene of pure gould, and he had had measure for measure, yea aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, heauens remuneration heaped vpon him in lieu of Christian perfection, if he had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him selfe, and abandoned the worlds trashe, to haue partaked with Christ, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens treasure.</p>
               <p>And yet this being a <hi>counsayle</hi> not a <hi>precept,</hi> it is not enioyned as a precept to all, but giuen by way of <hi>counsayle</hi> vnto perfiter men, as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers teache. And the reason is excellently ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by <hi>S.</hi> GREGORY the great, to be this. <hi>It is not enioyned as a precept to all (for then vvere it sinne either to marry, or to possesse any of the vvorlds goods) but yet it is counsayled vnto men of more holy ranke;</hi> For these haue an arbitrary, and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary choyce in their things.</p>
               <p>Such were the Apostles, and those Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall men, that hauing possessiōs, sould them, brought in the money and layde it downe at the Apostles feete.<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Such was holy <hi>Antony</hi> that ancient Monke of Egypt; <hi>S. Paul</hi> the Heremite; <hi>S. Benedict; S. Hierom; S. Basill; S. Gregory Nazianzen; S. Gregory</hi> the great; <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> and many other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177048:14"/> Doctours, and Fathers; the most renowned lights of learning, and greatest pillars of the Church.</p>
               <p>And was not Christ him selfe Maister, and <hi>Regius Professor</hi> of this <hi>spirituall</hi> poverty? spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall I call it, because the contempt of this world for the hope of heauen, is the worke of Gods spirit, wrought within our soules. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his entrance into this world, when his house was a stable, his cradle a cratch; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his continuance in the world, lyuing mearely vpon almes ministred vnto him by certaine godly women, and deuout persons. VVitnesse his complaint; <hi>the foxes haue holes, and the birds of heauen haue nests, but the sonne of man hath not, vvhereon to rest his head.</hi> And was he any richer at his departure out of this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, when wanting a sepulcher of his owne, he was enterred in an other mans tombe?</p>
               <p>Finally; though he were lord, and owner of all (being God the lord, and creator of all) and the sole heyre-apparant of heauen, and earth; yet was he content to forsake all: of rich he became poore, teaching aswell <hi>opere,</hi> as <hi>ore,</hi> by example of lyuing, as manner of teaching; reall practising,<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> as orall instructing; <hi>first doing,</hi> &amp; <hi>then teaching;</hi> and all to this end, <hi>vt conuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio magistri forma esset discipuli;</hi> as blessed LEO speaketh;<note place="margin">Ser. 5. de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uit. Christi.</note> that is, that he might generally
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177048:14"/> weane all Christians from the loue of this world; but especially, that he might become vnto his disciples, and all Apostolicall men, a perfit patterne of this spirituall poverty; the maisters conuersation being the schollers best instruction.</p>
               <p>For Christ came not downe from heauen to earth, from the bosome of the Father, by his eternall generation, GOD, to the wombe of his Mother, by temporall incarnation, MAN; when he deigned to stoope downe so lowe, nay vouchafed <hi>exinanire seipsum,</hi> to put of the garment of his Fathers, and heauens glory, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uesting his incomprehensible deity with the base raggs of finite mortality; I say Christ did not performe all this onely to fulfill the morall Decalogue, but ouer, and aboue the lawes righteousnesse, he taught that,<note place="margin">See S. Basill. de vera vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginit.</note> which the law wanted of the merit of perfection.</p>
               <p>And as he taught this vnto vs by practise in his owne most sacred person, and in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of his Apostles, so he left vs the first pure primitiue Church, and raysed vp many in the other succeeding ages and Centuries of the Catholique Church, to be examples, and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of these <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the summe of my Repetition, with a more ample explanation of my former Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; iustified now in publique against the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177048:15"/> Brethren, who had traduced it in their whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering conuenticles, according to the liberty of their priuate spiritts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII. D. HVTTON</hi> his kitchin-conference vvith me vpon the deliuery of this last sermon.</head>
               <p>THIS sermon being ended, and supper time immediately approaching; M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Hutton</hi> (one of the Channons of <hi>Christ-Church;</hi> now deputed <hi>Prouicechancellour</hi> in the absence of M. Doctour <hi>King</hi>) sent for me by one of my fellow Chaplaines into the cōmon kitchin,<note place="margin">A place fitt to treat vpō Iouinianis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; but vnfit for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> to conferre with me vpon the point deliuered in my sermon.</p>
               <p>Hither I no sooner came, but, he (interes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himselfe in the quarrell of IOVINIAN) beganne very fiercely to assault, &amp; chardge me for preaching <hi>scandalous,</hi> &amp; <hi>erroneous</hi> doctrine; excepting farther against the termes of <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Chastity,</hi> and <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; expressely mentioned by me in the aforesaid sermon.</p>
               <p>The onset being thus giuen by his worshipp, my warde was; Sir. (vnder your correction) the doctrine lately by me preached (howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177048:15"/> you disconceipt it) is not, nay cannot pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly be either <hi>scandalous,</hi> or <hi>erroneous;</hi> for it is the doctrine of that great Pillar of the Latine Church <hi>S. Gregory;</hi> accorded vnto, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by vniforme consent of fathers, both of the <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>As for the termes of<note n="a" place="margin">Vigrinity equalleth it selfe to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells; yea, if vve examine vvell the matter, vve shall find it to exceede Angells; for that cōtrary to nature, it getteth a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory in flesh aboue flesh, vvhich An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels do not. Cypr. de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no pudicitiae</note>
                  <hi>Angelicall Chastity;</hi> &amp; <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes</hi> of perfection, I haue not hammered them vpon any anuile in the forge of my owne braine, but rather borrowed them from Orthodox Antiquity.</p>
               <p>Against this he replyed;<note place="margin">Virginity (an Angelicall guift) excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as an Angell excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth a man. Damasc. li. 4. Orthodoxae fidei, cap. 25. Vide Cypr. de natiuitate Christi &amp; Hieron. lib. 1. contra Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian.</note> that if I preached any erroneous doctrine out of <hi>S. Gregory</hi> (such as this must needes be) then both the defence of the doctrine, and Authour himselfe would be required at my hands. For (sayd he) cannot <hi>Gregory</hi> haue his errours, but you must broach them here to infect this place with POPERY?</p>
               <p>This was the accompte, that the culinarian Doctour made of S. GREGORY the great; one of the holiest, &amp; learnedst doctours, that euer breathed in the CATHOLIQVE Church;<note place="margin">Ildephonse de viris illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribus ca. 1. Isidore de viris illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cap. 2. Vide Greg. Turon. lib. 20. Histor. de laudibuat Gregorij.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling <hi>S. Antony</hi> in holinesse, <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> in elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quēce, <hi>S. Augustin</hi> in wisedome; ful of cōpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiō, humility, the grace &amp; feare of God; indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with such light of knowledge, that not any of the present time was equal vnto, no nor of the former: to whose moral expositiō of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all the doctours giue place, &amp; that in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177048:16"/> iudgment of a generall councell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Concilium Toletan.</note>Did it then become M. Doctour HVTTON to detract from the due worth of so great, &amp; learned a Saint? since I may yet adde this to perfit his prayse; <hi>vvhatsoeuer he vvas vnto others, doubtlesse vnto vs he vvas an Apostle</hi> (to speake in the phrase of the Apostle) to whom our EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LISH nation standeth perpetually obliged for her cōuersion from Paganisme vnto the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian faith.<note place="margin">Beda, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siast. Histor. Angl. lib. 2. cap. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But to passe ouer the praise of this bright shininge starre in the firmamēt of the Church; my reioynder was, that this doctrine must first be prooued to be <hi>erroneous</hi> &amp; <hi>scandalous</hi> before any such imputation ought (vppon absolute necessity) to be imposed, and fastened vpon it, since <hi>scandall</hi> doth arise from errour, &amp; errour is an approbation of that, which is false in iudgment, and vnderstanding.</p>
               <p>And as for defending of <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion then was, &amp; now is, that the very name, it self, &amp; Authority of this worthy Father ought and would rather (amongst all learned, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious deuines) be my iust defence and full dischardge, then that his credit should be so farre called into questiō, as now (after a 1000. yeares continuance in the Catholique Church of Christ: being generally reputed <hi>Orthodox</hi> so longe) to stand in need of myne, or any other
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177048:16"/> manns defence whatsoeuer.</p>
               <p>And yet rather then the doctrine shal be thus odiously traduced, and my Authour want his promerited defence, I will according to that poore ability (wherwith God hath ēabled me) endeuour to defend both it, &amp; him: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if <hi>S. Gregory,</hi> in this point, hath not trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed the bounds of ANCIENTER Church, nor crossed any tenent of his owne PRESENT Church, nor yet, for this, hath hitherto bene censured by the laufull iudgement of any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique SVCCEDING Church: nay if the Church more ancient then his, his owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, &amp; the euer after succeding Centuries of <hi>Catholique</hi> Church haue, from hand to hand, deliuered vnto him, receaued with him, and with vniforme consent followed him in this point of doctrine, neuer so much as once no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, questioning it, impugning it, contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it (which certainly they would haue done, had the doctrine bene erroneous: for their deuoted piety spared no Heretick,<note place="margin">Origē Mill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nar; Tertull. Mōtanising Cypr. rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tising.</note> no not the moste renowned martirs, nor glorious fathers of the Church in any of their errours, repugnāt vnto the vnity of Catholique verity) then, vpon these premises, I may irrefragably conclude in defence of my Authour, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that <hi>S. Gregory</hi> his position is no priuate opinion hatched out of his owne brayne, but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177048:17"/> the vniforme deduction, &amp; tradition of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his spouse the true <hi>Catholique,</hi> neuer errin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churche inspired, guided, &amp; directed by Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his holy spirit in all ages.</p>
               <p>But M. Doctour <hi>Hutton</hi> lending a deafe ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto my defence (though in my conscience and iudgment, it ought to haue satisfied him sounded another alarome, and ringed a fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peale in my eares, chardging, nay surchar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging me <hi>(ad nauseam vsque)</hi> for houlding an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> distinction betwixt PRECEPTS and COVN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>SAILES. For (said he) there is no such distin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction: those, which you falsely call <hi>Counsayle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> are in deede <hi>Precepts</hi> and not <hi>Counsayles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was his definitiue resolution, sif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting out of the sieue of the Church all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wheaten meale, I meane the fine flower of sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Pouerty,</hi> Angelicall <hi>Chastity,</hi> and leauin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nought else within it, but the branne, and hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of <hi>Iouinian</hi> his heresy; which (to speake o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it in one word, as it deserueth) is the very eua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuation, &amp; exinanition of all the best fruicte of our Christian Religion. And this he di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with an earnest protestation; not being able t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> containe him selfe from vowing, &amp; solemne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> swearing <hi>before God,</hi> that he would send me v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to my Lorde Bishoppe of <hi>London,</hi> to answer the point before the highe Commission.</p>
               <p>To this I replied. Syr: the distinctiō betwix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177048:17"/>
                  <hi>Precepts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Counsailes</hi> is no deuise of mine, but the doctrine of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> grounded vpon Christ his restrictiue negatiue; <hi>non omnes capiūt:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>S. Paul</hi> had no precept: and vpon Christ his exhortatiue affirmatiue, <hi>qui potest capere, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Hereupon the Apostle giueth his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle; <hi>Consilium do:</hi> &amp; thus all ancient Church hath interpreted his sentence.</p>
               <p>But admit (by way of supposition) your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory conclusion, &amp; suppose that there be no counsayles, but let all be precepts; do they not then as PRECEPTS bind you, and that <hi>sub poenâ?</hi> For that which is a precept is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded; that which is cōmaunded, must be done of necessity; that, which must perforce be done, is punished being left vndone: and in vaine is that commaunded as necessary, which is left in the free choyce of the commaunded as voluntary as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> teacheth.<note place="margin">lib. 1 contra Iouinianu.</note> wherefore giue me leaue (without offence) to demaund; why do you, or any other marry, or possesse any of the worlds goods? ought your practise to be cōtrary to the precept? And doth not <hi>S. Gregory</hi> teache, that if counsailes were precepts, then were it sinne, &amp; that damnable too, to possesse any of the worlds goods? And were not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadge taken away (which is no lesse then flatt heresy) if virginity were a precept?<note place="margin">De vera virg.</note> as <hi>S. Basill</hi> and the Fathers teach.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177048:18"/>
               <p>This I demanded; but he then passed it oue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with silence; &amp; therefore I expect his answere nou, how he can avoyd this consequence which followeth vpon his owne learning.</p>
               <p>As for sending me vpp to <hi>London,</hi> to answere the point there, my reply was; that, for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part, I was ready to answere vnto the point and to iustify the doctrine either there, or els<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where in what consistory soeuer in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Onely for your owne credit sake, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place (sayd I) which you supply, I wish that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would please you to be better aduised; at leas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to conferre with some other doctours, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heard the sermon aswell as your selfe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turely to deliberate, whether there be <hi>scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum datum,</hi> or <hi>acceptum,</hi> a scandall on my par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iustly giuen, or on your part vniustly taken; &amp; whether your exception against my doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will beare waight, or no, being poysed in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indifferent ballance of equity; before you re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solue vpon this precipitation. Otherwayes you shall bewray great want of sound iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in opinion, and disclose much ouersigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in discretion.</p>
               <p>And farther; I assure you; call me whithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you will into question, I shall discardge my se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with sufficient credit, when you shall gayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little by questioning my doctrine or molestin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me causelesly.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177048:18"/>
               <p>Here the kitchin-conference brake vp: onely, in the loose, he required a copy of that doctrine of <hi>Counsailes</hi> deliuered by me out of <hi>S. Gregory.</hi> To this I voluntarily cōdescended: adding these words to intimate my confident resolution. Sir. <hi>For the doctrine, I vvill request no favour at your hands: only I hope that you vvill do me iustice: if not, assure your selfe, I shall right my selfe elsevvhere.</hi> This was the last period of our conference at that time: &amp; so we parted: sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per calling vs both away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Hovv <hi>D. Hutton,</hi> receyuing a copy of the aforesayd Sermon, found no matter of exception against me. His precipitate course hindered by the aduise of a learned, and iudicious Deuine.</head>
               <p>SOME two dayes following (vpon the very point of the prefixed time, which doctour <hi>Hutton</hi> had appointed) I deliuered vnto him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in his owne lodging) a punctuall summe, &amp; copy of the doctrine, so vehemently by him excepted against, and so earnestly required.</p>
               <p>The said copy, with all seeming alacrity he chearfully, and contentedly receiued at my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177048:19"/> hands, dismissing me without any further questioning about the point, either then or any other time after. VVherupon I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he had retracted his former opinion, by a more prudent circumspection.</p>
               <p>And that he now determined to pursue me no farther, I was then, and am now the rather induced to belieue, because, on the very night of our sayd kitchin-conference, he repayred vnto a very graue, and learned Doctour in that Vniuersity (who had heard my sermon) to craue his opinion, and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution concerning the point; complayning first of my peremptory, and obstinate resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; discouering withall his disgust of the Doctrine; certifying him farther of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to send me vp to the Bishoppe of <hi>London</hi> to answere the point there.</p>
               <p>The venerable Doctour perceauing his headdy resolution, and withall conceiuing the truth of the Doctrine (which his discreete and mature iudgment could not possibly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to dissemble) very prudently, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly aduised him to stirre no more in the point; but to passe it ouer with a calme, and quiet silence. For (said he) in sending him vppe to <hi>London,</hi> well you may put him to trouble and chardge: but for the Doctrine (for ought that I could conceiue) the issue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177048:19"/> will be this: he may, and will answere it either here, there, or else where, with more credit, then you shall possibly gayne in calling it into question.</p>
               <p>And is this (sayd he) the rewarde of our pulpit paynes? Are schollers, whose state you know to be but meane, to be put by schollers vnto this extraordinary chardge, needelesse, and causelesse expense? Ought not you, and I, and all of our ranke, rather study to giue them all lawfull content, then to seeke their greiuances, by surmising against them vniust matter; taking exception, where no scandall is giuen, to bring them to iust discontent? wherefore (Maister Subdeane) to waste nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more time, nor words about this point; for conclusion (since, as you say, you are come purposely to aske my opinion and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle in this matter) my aduise is (if you will be ruled by me) let all matters be husht; rest as they are; and there an end, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout either further troubling, or prouoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him.</p>
               <p>Thus the good Doctour soundly, plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely, and, on all parts, charitably afforded him his freindly aduise. And herevpon it was, that Doctour <hi>Hutton</hi> was satisfied; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof he gaue sufficient signes, when he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the aforesaid copy.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177048:20"/>
               <p>So the matter was, for that time, ended; and the doctrine, without any manner of preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, or farther contradiction, cleared: being now at two seuerall tymes by me preached, First generally glanced at, &amp; intimated only: Secondly, against the <hi>Brethren</hi> (who in priuate corners traduced it) publiquely r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peated, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, and explaned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Hovv, vpon <hi>M. Prouicechancellours</hi> cessation to prosecute me any farther, <hi>D. Benefield</hi> in a publick, solemne Lecture, did mainely impugne the aforesaid doctrine; vvith shevv of particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions against me for the same.</head>
               <p>AND now resolued, as my next occasion drew me to preach, to proceede forwards with the exposition of my text, and to haue vnfolded the sense of <hi>the opening of those mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes;</hi> the booke of conscience, and the booke of God his eternall prescience; for so it followed in my text; <hi>the bookes vvere opened, and an other booke vvas opened; vvhich is the booke
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177048:20"/> of lyfe.</hi> This was my intention; because I had now spoken sufficiently of that point (as I thought) which I mett withall but <hi>obiter</hi> in my text, vpon a subdiuision, and a distinction ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted foorth of <hi>S. Gregory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I resolued priuately vpon this course, so I had performed accordingly, if a certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant accident had not interrupted, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed this my quiet, and setled resolution; diuerting my purpose (for that present) and conuerting my forces an other way. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion wherof was, as followeth.</p>
               <p>In the Easter terme following <hi>M. Benefield</hi> (one of the Inceptors of deuinity for the Act ensuing) whether it were of his owne proper motion (which I very hardly can suppose) or vpon the instigatiō of some other of the BRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THREN (which I do more easily belieue; since he must needes go, whom a maine schisme dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) purposedly prouided one of his six so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne lectures (read for the assumpt of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Doctourshippe) mainely, and directly by way of opposition, and confutation of that erroneous <hi>Popish</hi> doctrine. For so it pleased this <hi>initiate Doctour</hi> to brand the Doctrine of all the Ancient <hi>Catholique</hi> Doctours,<note place="margin">A nevv Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford cōtrary to all the Catholick Doctours of the Church.</note> deliuered concerning EVANGELICALL COVNSAILES. VVherein whether I, and my doctrine were mainely shott at and impugned or no, I will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177048:21"/> not iudge in my owne cause; let the equall, and impartiall Reader vmpire for vs both.</p>
               <p>This businesse was not so secretly plotted by the aforesaid <hi>Brethren,</hi> not yet so priuately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and caried by the Actor himselfe, but I had certaine notice giuen me by a friend of mine (a graue Bachellour in diuinity,<note place="margin">M. R.</note> and a man of good esteme) who was acquainted both with the proiect, and the day of lecture: wherof he gaue me a particular intimation.</p>
               <p>This lecture I both heard, and noted in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. But such an other lecture, so false, so He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, with such violent wresting of sacred write, such impudent reiecting of holy fathers, quite besides the drifte of the one, and cleane contrary to the resolution of the other, I sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or neuer heard in that famous, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Academy.</p>
               <p>The text by him treated vpon was; <hi>go sell all that thou hast, and giue to the poore, and thou shalt haue treasure in heauen; and come, and follovv me.</hi> A maine ground, and pregnant text (as I take it; and I take it aright, if all ancient Church mistake it not) to builde vpp rather, then to batter downe; to confirme rather, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes.</hi> The Fathers which he cited, &amp; named to stand for <hi>Counsailes</hi> were diuers: he might haue vrged all, both of the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Church; all of them being
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177048:21"/> resolute for COVNSAILES (&amp; that vpon those woords of our Sauiour; <hi>goe sell all</hi> &amp;c. As also vpon that distinctiō of the Apostle; <hi>Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning virgins I haue no precept from our Lord; but I giue my aduise;</hi> or <hi>Counsaile</hi>) which is a weaghty consideration, if their ioynt consent and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme authority might haue borne any sway with this noble Inceptour.</p>
               <p>But this nouitiate DOCTOVR (if yet he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue that title, who dealt thus rudely with the true DOCTOVRS of the Church) as he peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the sacred writt of God (his reuealed in will his word) so reiected the FATHERS, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting them all with this one hereticall breath, that <hi>they vvere all bevvitched, deceiued, and caried avvay as men vvith the errours of the time vvherein they lyued.</hi> Thus <hi>Caluin, Luther,</hi> the foure good fellow <hi>Germans</hi> (who composed their false, &amp; fond <hi>Centuries</hi> in a stoue of <hi>Magdeburge</hi>) taught their nouice to blaspheme. O times, ô ages wherein we now liue; when <hi>Caluin, Luther,</hi> foure carousing <hi>Almans</hi> (nay rather Ale-men) and one puny doctour, dare thus openly (in the eares of Christendome, &amp; in the publique eye of so famous an vniuersity) blaspheme God his holy spirit, promised by Christ to lodge in the bosome of these venerable, and sober aged <hi>Fathers,</hi> chiefe pillars of the <hi>holy Catholique Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177048:22"/>
               <p>And yet after he had thus censoriously han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled the FATHERS,<note place="margin">This is right the Puritan cutt: as D. Bancroft obserueth against the Presbyterian factiō, in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vvhole, Chapters of his Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay.</note> vpon my priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferēce with him, in stead of the Fathers, which I called for, he offred vnto me two <hi>English</hi> pamphlets; one wherof was entituled <hi>the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of the Church of England;</hi> whereat I could not but smile, in regard of his simplicity, though inwardly grieued much at the times misery, when a statizing Pamphleter (who would flye vpon the wing of his penne vnto the height of some ambitious designment) shall be compared, nay preferred before the ancient Orthodox deuines, that painefully la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in the vineyard of the Church against the brunt of al Heresies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Hovv the indignity, and leuity of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd Lecture, prouoked me to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse a more ample defence of my doctrine.</head>
               <p>THIS solemne lecture, read in publicke schooles by an Inceptor in deuinity for so venerable a degree, enforced me now (euen as I would not openly betray the truth of this doctrine) vnto a more plaine, ample, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall defence; inuiting me also, nay infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177048:22"/> me with some extraordinary desire, for the reiection, and depulsion of his infirme reasons.</p>
               <p>And though diuers of my best frends (whose intreaty in any other matter, might haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled with me) dissuaded me from this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise (as being to full of perill) fearing the violence of the time, and the manifould dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that by this resolution I stoode likely to expose my selfe vnto, yet ten thousand such like motiues of terrour could not detayne me, nor deterre my resolution. For a higher hand then humane (euen the hand of heauen) so ouerruled me (cōmanding, nay coūtermaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all my affections that way) that partly the pure zeale, and entire affection (which I euer bare vnto the blessed FATHERS; being wholly indebted vnto them for that little which I haue) and partly my deuoted loue vnto many of that VNIVERSITY; whom I could not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently suffer to be thus peruerted in so mayne a doctrine, tending to all Religious piety; and lastly the perfit hatred, that from my inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most soule, I euer conceiued against <hi>Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme</hi> (the very bane of ancient Christianity) these I say, and the like motiues (to recollect them alltogether) could not suffer me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the shipwracke of all conscience, to sit still and to be silent, whilst God his eternal truth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177048:23"/> Christ his holy direction, &amp; the perpetuall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the <hi>Catholick</hi> mother-Church were so publickly impugned, and so notoriously prophaned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Reg. 26.</note>Thefore as <hi>Abishai,</hi> out of his loue to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed king, sayd vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by on blow (surely layd on) to end all quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and him,<note place="margin">Benefield, vvithall his comperes.</note>
                  <hi>let me strike him but once, yea nayle him to the earth vvith a speare, seing God hath thus closed him into thy hands and I vvill strike him no more;</hi> euen so (to apply the words onely; for I iustify not the intended fact of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishai</hi>) my loue vnto the king of heauen (when I purposed by one other blowe soundly giuen, to end this controuersity) forced me to cry within my heart; <hi>let me strike him but once and I vvill strike him no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if this blowe haue not hit home to the finall deciding of this quarrell, depriuing his heresy of all breathing, let him, or any, or all his complices (and especially those six well se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected doctours, who haue so farre engaged their credits by interessing themselues so dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely in the quarrell) warde, and answere the blow which they haue publickly receiued, for all of them put together haue not yet diuerted the stroke. Or if the cause, which the principal Act or vndertooke,<note place="margin">Doctour Benefielde.</note> will abide so much as the least touchstone of tryall, let him, vpon what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177048:23"/> grounds, and confidence soeuer he standeth as I dare boldly chardge, and challendg him he stādeth vpon none, but hereticall) diuulge his lecture vnto the sensure of the world.</p>
               <p>Meane while, for the honour of God, and confusion of Sathan, to preserue Christ his word (the word of verity) from the infection of Heresy; for the iust defence of this doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the due reproofe of hereticall innouation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue thought good here to insert a true copy of the Sermon preached by me in <hi>Oxford</hi> to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify EVANGELICALL COVNSAILES vpon the occasion aboue mentioned.<note place="margin">anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. 1608. 27. die Iunij.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Reade it (deare Christian brother) seuerly iudge of it impartially; and God graunt it may effect in thee what I wish hartily: and that is (if thou feelest thy selfe called, &amp; thy soule moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued effectually) to practise the same. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177048:24"/>
               <head>The sermon preached in defence of <hi>Euangelicall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayles,</hi> and the Fathers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND <hi>I sawe the dead, both great, and sma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> stande before God, and the bookes were opened and another booke was opened,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 20.12.</note>
                  <hi>which is the booke of life, and the dead were iudged of those thinges, which were written in the bookes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their woorks.</hi> This verse naturallie floweth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to three streames, of Christian Doctrine: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a generall citation of all; <hi>and I sawe the dead, bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great and small stand before God.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The second is a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer examination of all, vppon a twoofould eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence brought in: <hi>liber conscientiae, librum praescientia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the booke of conscience, and the booke of God his aeternall prescience: <hi>the bookes were opened, and another booke was opened, which is the booke of life;</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A finall retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, inuolued in the acte, and particuler manner of the iudgment; <hi>and the deade were iudged of those things, which were written in the bookes accordinge t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their woorkes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>generall citation,</hi> more particulerlie wrappeth in it the persons appearing; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>the dead:</hi> the extent of this appearaunce; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <hi>great, and small:</hi> subiection to this throane; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>stande</hi> together with the iudge, before whom this grande appearaunce is made; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> GOD: <hi>and I sawe the dead both great and small stande before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the personns appearing, summoned by Christe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177048:24"/> his imperiall power commaunding, and produced by Angells voluntarie ministering, and all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res necessarie obeying, <hi>(sea, death, and hell surrendring their dead)</hi> I haue already spoken; as also of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of this appearaunce; subiection to this throa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and of the Iudge before whome this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is made.</p>
               <p>In the extent of this appearaunce I noted a fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refoulde acception of <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIRSTE <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small</hi> for worldlie authoritie, and tēporall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> SECONDLIE <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small,</hi> in respect of heauenlie supereminencie of grace, and spirituall infusion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> THIRDLIE <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small,</hi> in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of diuersitie of rewards, and retribution. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> FOVRTHLIE <hi>great</hi> and <hi>small,</hi> in regard of dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, yea contrarietie also of woorkes, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>And from this last signification, arose that foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foulde distinction of <hi>S. Gregorie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">26. lib. in Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 24.25.</note>
                  <hi>quidam non iudican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; pereunt; quidam iudicantur, &amp; pereunt; quidam iudicantur, &amp; regnant; quidam non iudicantur, &amp; regnant.</hi> That is (as another auncient writer, commentinge vppon my text, fitlie rendereth it) some are not iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged but condemned allreadie; perishing without further iudgment; some are to be iudged, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; perishing by iudgment; some are to be iudged, and saued; saued by iudgment; some are iudged and saued allreadie; saued without iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The first ranke are suche, <hi>whose damnation sleepeth not,</hi> but is allreadie certain:<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>Qui non credit in filio Dei</hi> IAM <hi>iudicatus est;</hi> he that beleeueth not in the sonne of God is allreadie condemned, being thereto or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and predestinated; <hi>ad poenam, non ad culpam;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177048:25"/> ad supplicium, non ad peccatum, ad mortem animae, non impietatis primam, sed ad mortem animae, damnationis se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam:</hi> as that mellifluous Father <hi>Fulgentius</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth:<note place="margin">De predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione ad monimum.</note> that is, to penaltie, not to iniquitie; to the wages of sinne, not to the guilte of sinne; not to the first death of the soule, that is transgression, but to the second death of the soule, to wit certaine dānation. For ther sinns (being loude crying sinns) crie with <hi>Sodome</hi> in the eares of heauen; <hi>are open before hande, and goe before them vnto iudgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pinn: 5.24.</note>The second sort are suche, whose damnation is yet vncertaine; for admit, that they be nowe in the state of damnation, yet let them turne from ther sinns, God will turne from his wrathe: he offereth them heauen, and threateneth them hell: he setteth <hi>life, and death, good and euill, before them:</hi> let them reache out their hand, &amp; choose whether they wil.</p>
               <p>He that woulde not the deathe of a sinner, (for our mercifull God, would haue <hi>all to be saued</hi>) offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth meanes of saluation, vnto these sinners; knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king outwardlie, inwardlie, by the operation of his woorde, by the inspiration of his spirit, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie doore, of ther drousie consciences, to awaken them (if it be possible) from the dead sleepe, and lethargie of sinne: opening their eyes some times, and inlardging their harts, that, if they will, they may come to repentaunce, and amendement of life, <hi>out of the snare of the deuill, who are taken of him at his will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which meanes of their conuersion, proceeding from his meere compassion (which should leade them to compunction) if they refuse, <hi>and after the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hardnes of hart that cannot repent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note>
                  <hi>treasure vppe wrathe against the day of wrathe,</hi> then are they taken of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177048:25"/> at his will. Hence springeth the secōd braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; <hi>some are iudged,</hi> and condemned. These happilie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noughe they haue not sinned with so highe a hand against heauen, as the former haue done; yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie haue they so greiued the spirit, which should haue <hi>sealed them vppe vnto the day of redemption,</hi> and so highlie haue they offended the Maiestie of heauen, that <hi>their sinns followe them vnto iudgment;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. tim. 5.24.</note> nay dogge them, as a sergeant at heeles, to arreste them.</p>
               <p>The third sort are suche, whose saluation is not yet certaine, <hi>certitudine rei,</hi> thoughe it be <hi>spei;</hi> not <hi>sui,</hi> though <hi>Dei:</hi> with certaintie of reall possessiō, though it be of spirituall expectation; with anie certaintie arising from themselues, but with a certaintie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding frō God. Gods promises are conditionall, &amp; his election infalliblie implieth in it, nay poynteth vnto the verie meanes of our saluation; his aeternall prescience so directing the decree of his Counsayle.</p>
               <p>These thoughe they stande,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.12.</note> yet must they <hi>take heede lest they fall.</hi> For these are but yet <hi>in via,</hi> not <hi>in patria;</hi> vppon the seas of this worlde, flotinge, not in the hauen of heauen, raigninge. Beginne they in the spirit? Yet <hi>they must not end in the fleshe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Galat. 3.3.</note>
                  <hi>or be made perfit by the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>she.</hi> For they are yet in <hi>certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> not in <hi>triumpho,</hi> warfaring on earthe, encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed with theiues and pirats, the worlde, fleshe, an deuill on all sides assaultinge them; not trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phinge in heauen, enuironed and garded, with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Angells, and armies of the spirits of iust &amp; perfit men.</p>
               <p>These must remember, and remembring tremble at that fearfull distriction, and terrible commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (so often reiterated and direfullie threatned by the prophet.) <hi>If the righteous turne away from his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177048:26"/> righteousnes, and commit iniquitie, and doe according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the abominations, that the wicked man doth, shall he li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> saithe the Lorde God of hoasts? All his righteousnes, that he hath done, shall not be mentioned, but in his transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, that he hath committed, and in his sinne, that he hath sinned, in them shall he die.</hi> And the reason is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlie rendred by the Apostle:<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.5.6.</note>
                  <hi>For it is impossible, that they which were once enlightened, and haue tasted of the heauenlie guifte, and were made partakers of the holie ghoaste, and haue tasted of the good woorde of God, and of the powers of the worlde to come, if they fall awaye, should be renewed by repentance, seing they crucifie againe to them selues the sonne of God and make a mocke of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I speake not this (my Brethren) to shake the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, of anie soules saluation, rightlie builte on gods election, but to giue a caueat to all (a caueat indeede, and a terrible one too) to dehort vs from all sinfull secure presumption of heauen, lest from the steepe pitche of an ouerweening securitie, and presuming certaintie, we tumble headlonge downe into hell, as also a motiue, to exhort, and stirre vs vppe all, <hi>to make our callinge, and el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction sure by woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out our saluation with feare, and tremblinge.</hi> For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and perseueraunce onlie sealeth vnto vs the assuraunce of our saluation, since truthe that cannot lye, nor deceaue, hath plainlie taught vs; <hi>he that continueth vnto the end he shalbe saued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The last sort are suche, whose saluation is already certain; and these differ from the other, <hi>quoad gradū; gradum in via, perfectionis; gradum in patria, retributionis.</hi> For if <hi>stella a stella differt gloria</hi> (the Apostle applieth it to the bodilie resurrection) that is,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 15.41.</note> if ther be degrees of exaltation in the kingdome of glorie; of necessitie, by force of ineuitable consequence, it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177048:26"/> must followe, that there be degrees of Christian perfection in the kingdome of grace, the one being a retribution of the other; heauens remuneration awarded, accordinge to Christian perfection pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised.</p>
               <p>These ioyne <hi>with their faithe, vertue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. pet. 1.5.6.7.10.</note>
                  <hi>with vertue knowledge, with knowledge temperaunce; with tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce patience, with patience, godlines; with godlines, brotherlie kindnes; with brotherlie kindnes,</hi> loue; the verie bonde of perfection, nay <hi>plíroma tou nomou;</hi> the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fillinge of the lawe; and <hi>doing these things they can neuer fall.</hi> These giue all diligence to make their callinge, and election sure by faithe, by woorkes, by precepts, by Counsailes. These are <hi>terrestres An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geli, coelestes homines,</hi> earthlie Angells, heauenlie men: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir names are written in heauen, and them selues registred, and enrolled, in the booke of life, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he lambe. These (I remember well) I stiled <hi>entiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anscendentia,</hi> men soaring with the wings of faithe and woorkes, aboue the ordinarie pitche of men: <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam praecepta legis perfectiori virtute transcendentes;</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cending, surmountinge the precepts of the lawe, by Euangelicall Counsailes of greater perfection: so speaketh <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> in the place aboue cited.</p>
               <p>For explanation of which sentence of that good Father, and great pillar of the <hi>Latine</hi> Churche wee are to note, that precepts and Counsailes, may be considered comparatiuelie two manner of wayes; viz. either GENERALLIE, comparing all the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts</hi> of the lawe ioyntlie with the <hi>Counsailes</hi> of the gospell seuerallie, or PARTICVLARLY, by comparing seuerall <hi>Counsailes</hi> of the gospell, not with <hi>euerie,</hi> or with <hi>all</hi> the precepts of the lawe ioyntly in one aggregate bodie, but seuerallie with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177048:27"/> the precepts conuersant <hi>circa eandem materiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 119.</note>In the first consideration, I stand not to iustifie those woords of <hi>S. Gregorie, transcendunt aliqui praecept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> legis perfectiori virtute.</hi> For <hi>mandatum tuum nimis latu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Domine:</hi> thy commaundement, ô Lorde, <hi>is exceding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> broad:</hi> yea so broad, that the lawe alone, <hi>lex imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culata,</hi> that vndefiled lawe of God, containeth in it, prima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilie, originallie, essentiallie, all kinde of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian perfection; and it was neuer that orthodoxe Fathers meaninge so to compare them. But in the later consideration, most true are those woordes of S. Gregorie; <hi>transcendunt aliqui praecepta legis perfection virtute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To illustrate this comparison by example. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> FIRST compare that Euangelicall Counsaile, <hi>vade, vend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> omnia, &amp; da pauperibus, &amp; sequere me,</hi> with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>non furaberis:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And SECONDLIE cōpare tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Euangelicall Counsaile of virginitie,<note place="margin">Math: 19.11.</note>
                  <hi>qui potest caper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> capiat.</hi> (Which Luther himselfe in the 30. artic. of his assertion held to be the onlie Euāgelicall Counsaile) with that precept, <hi>non moechaberis:</hi> then you shall see euidently, that an higher degree of perfection is in the action cōformable to those twoo <hi>Counsailes,</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the actions inioyned in the other two <hi>Precepts.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in actions there must needes be <hi>degrees</hi> of goodnes witnesse some actions good in a meane degree of goodnes; as not to hate his owne fleshe, to require good for good, not to steale, not to cōmitte adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp;c. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wherein I may demaund with our Sauiour <hi>what singular thinge is done?</hi> doe not publicans do the same? Did not blind foulded gentilisme do these things? Other actions there are, which are good in a higher degree of goodnes: such are the actions perfourmed in the <hi>Counsailes</hi> of voluntarie pouertie,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177048:27"/> virginitie, and the like.</p>
               <p>All perfection of man here, as it is in the waye of perfection to the seruice of God, is not equall, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the Apostles forsaking all, and followinge Christe: did all do so that beleiued in Christe? Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the first feruour, and zeale, of the primitiue Churche (newly founded, in the bloud of Christe, and watered in the bloud of his Apostles) selling all their possessions, without the least reseruatiō of any parte, and layinge downe the whole price therof at the Apostles feete; witnesse. <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in his 18.<note place="margin">Cap. 11.</note> sermon de <hi>verbis Apostoli:</hi> where that good Father speaketh thus in the person of certain virgins (in his time) religiouslie deuoted, and consecrated vnto the entire seruice of their God. <hi>Quod iubes, ne adulterae simus, hoc praecipis:</hi> amando <hi>te plus facimus quàm iubes.</hi> Wheras thou commaundest vs not to cōmitt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, this thou giuest vs in chardge by waye of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept; but in louing thee, wee doe more then thou cōmaundest. Witnesse learned,<note place="margin">He meaneth in this pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar kind.</note> and iudicious <hi>Hooker</hi> in the second booke of his <hi>Churche Politie,</hi> in the thirde page before the ende of the same booke: Witnesse also the <hi>Apologie</hi> in defence of him, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Doctor <hi>Couell;</hi> in the fourten the chapter; <hi>of satisfaction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The perfection of man here in this life, is the soules vnion with God; not <hi>essentiall,</hi> (for this is peculiar onely to the Trinitie.) Not <hi>personall</hi> (this proper to Christe his humanitie.) Not <hi>sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> (this extendeth to the whole Churche in generall.) But it is, <hi>vnio animae spiritualis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ber. in psal. 23.</note> the soules spirituall vnion with God, when the soule is wholly sequestred from the worlde, and is syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerelie rauished with the loue of God, of Christe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177048:28"/> and of her neighbour; guided, and ledde ther vnto by <hi>precepts,</hi> and <hi>Counsailes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which precepts, and Counsailes, thoughe they perfourme this, yet doe they diuerslie direct there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, according to the diuersitie of those things, about which they are conuersaunt; differinge onlie in <hi>modo,</hi> and not in <hi>re.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To explaine this point. Some things are cōtrarie to the loue of God, wherwith Charitie, and the loue of God, can haue no more agreement, then light &amp; darknes, God and <hi>Beliall,</hi> the Arke and <hi>Dagon, Baal</hi> his false preists, and <hi>Eliah</hi> the lordes true Prophet. And for remoouing these forthe of the waye of perfection, precepts are mainely giuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ber. ser. 35. 36. paruorum sermonum.</note>Other things are <hi>impedimenta charitatis,</hi> or <hi>impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta actus charitatis:</hi> that is, <hi>non illicita, sed impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta iustitiae;</hi> impediments of charitie, or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the acts of charitie, to witt not things sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie vnlawfull, but encombraunces vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes: &amp; for remoouing of these lettes, COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAILES are giuen.</p>
               <p>The first inioyneth abstinence from things sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie euill, &amp; vnlawfull, that cannot stande with the loue of God, nay contrarie to the loue of God, and of our neighbour. And for remoouing of these, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> PRECEPT is necessarie. The seconde commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not, but aduiseth abstinence, from things not simplie euill, nor in them selues vnlawfull; as <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and the <hi>riches</hi> of this worlde (the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God) but they may well stand with the loue of God; yet may they be so vsed, nay rather abused, that they may withdraw the minde from the loue of God.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 7.33.</note>
                  <hi>Qui duxit vxorem, curat quae sunt mundi:</hi> the married man careth for the things, that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177048:28"/> are of this worlde, &amp;c. Again; <hi>it is easier for a camell to passe throughe the eye of a needle, then for a riche man,</hi> that trusteth in his riches, (for so Christe expoundeth it) <hi>to enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Are not here <hi>marriage,</hi> and the consequences therof (necessarilie insuinge) <hi>riches,</hi> and the cares therof, <hi>impedimenta iustitiae,</hi> letts, and encombraunces vnto righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? And therfore these are left arbitrarie, and at our free choice, to be followed, or pretermitted, as euerie mans proper guift shalbe;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.7.</note>
                  <hi>vnusquisque suum habet donum;</hi> euerie man hath his proper guifte. So <hi>S. Hierom</hi> ad <hi>Eustochium;</hi> and against <hi>Iouinian, S. Ambrose,</hi> in the 10. booke of his Epistles; the 82. Epistle <hi>ad Vercellensem Ecclesiam;</hi> and in his tract <hi>de viduis, towards the ende. S. Augustine</hi> in his 61. sermon <hi>de tempore:</hi> the second booke of his <hi>Euangelicall que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions,</hi> chapter the 19. and in his <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> ad Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentium chapter the 121.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Counsailes</hi> therefore differ thus. PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEPTS are of necessitie; COVNSAILES arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, left to our free choice. Bothe ayme at the marke of heauē, by shootinge at the butte of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian perfection, but differ in the manner. Both leuell at the meanes of saluation: that is, perfection of charitie, yet Counsailes after a more exquisite, and excellinge perfection.</p>
               <p>The stage of this worlde, and the theater of the Churche present vnto our free choice the worlds trashe, and heauens true treasure, the more man cleaueth to heauens permanent felicitie, the more perfit, and excellent is he; nay to cast the worlds trashe wholly awaie in lue of heauens treasure, as seafaring men doe their goods and wares, in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of shipwracke, when the life is in hazarde, this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177048:29"/> is no precepte of necessitie, but onlie an aduise of greater perfection.</p>
               <p>Transgressors of the lawes <hi>precepts,</hi> deserue pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment; but they that perfourme not <hi>Counsailes</hi> sinne not; only they wāt some measure of perfectiō.</p>
               <p>Obseruers of <hi>Counsailes</hi> shall haue greater reward, yea they shall sit vppon throanes; &amp; not onlie iudge the twelue tribes of <hi>Israell,</hi> but doome both men &amp; Angells. It was Christ his promise of remuneration made to his disciples for their consolation, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to goe forwards with the practise of Christian perfection, embracing for his, &amp; heauens sake, voluntarie pouertie, virginall chastitie, and humble obedience. It was proclaymed also by that trumpet of the Apostles, preacher of the worlde, Apostle of the Gentiles, and descrier of heauenly mysteries, holie, and blessed <hi>S. Paul; knowe you not, that wee shall iudge the Angells?</hi> &amp;c. The woordes are so pregnant, that all the wrangling witts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious priuate spirits in the worlde cannot wrest them. But lawe breakers, without repētaunce, shall haue greater punishment.</p>
               <p>To shutte vppe all in one woorde; <hi>Precepts</hi> are exalted as necessary; <hi>Counsailes</hi> are offred as volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and arbitrarie. The one being done, is praysed, and highlie rewarded: the other being vndone, is reprehended, and punnished.</p>
               <p>This distinction betwixt <hi>precepts,</hi> and <hi>Counsailes,</hi> is no new Doctrine. <hi>S. Hierom</hi> ad <hi>Eustochium, de custodia virginitatis,</hi> and against <hi>Iouinian,</hi> layeth downe the pointe, and difference thus. <hi>VVhere there is a</hi> COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAILE, <hi>there is left a freedome; but</hi> PRECEPTS <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne a necessitie; precepts are common to all, Counsailes are the perfection of some fewe.</hi> (And this is agreeinge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177048:29"/> with that of <hi>Gregorie</hi> in the place aboue cited; <hi>non omnibus praecipiuntur, sed perfectioribus consuluntur:</hi> they are not commaunded to all, but aduised to men of the perfiter ranke.) <hi>Precepts obserued haue a rewarde, not obserued a punnishment; Counsailes not obserued haue no punnishment, but obserued haue a greater rewarde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to this purpose, almost in the verie selfe same woords speaketh S. AVGVSTINE in his 61. sermon <hi>de tempore:</hi> his 18. sermon <hi>de verbis Apostoli:</hi> his second booke of <hi>Euangelicall questions</hi> cap. 19. and in his <hi>Enchiridion ad Laurentium</hi> cap. 12. S. AMBROSE in the 10. booke of his Epistles, the 82. Epistle ad <hi>Vercellensem Ecclesiam;</hi> and his tract <hi>de viduis, propè fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> and generally the <hi>Greeke and Latine</hi> Fathers: such is the vniforme consent, and heauenlie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of all orthodoxe Antiquitie in this point of Doctrine.</p>
               <p>The defence therfore of <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes</hi> of perfectiō <hi>quoad viam,</hi> &amp; <hi>quoad gradum,</hi> which I would onlie commende vnto the learned &amp; iudicious (who well knowe that the whole course of Antiquitie, &amp; concurrence of the fathers do often mention them) is this; that <hi>there are in the gospell of Christe certaine</hi> COVNSAILES, <hi>which the Auncient pillers, &amp; Patriarches of diuinitie, call</hi> CONSILIA PERFECTIONIS <hi>Counsailes of perfection:</hi> and they are so called, <hi>non quòd ipsae sint per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiones, sed dispositiones quaedā ad perfectionem, quae cōstat in hoc, vt mens hominis Deo vacet:</hi> that is, not that they are in themselues perfections indeede, but rather dispositions, directions, preparations to perfection, which consisteth mainelie in this; that the soule (wholly sequestred from the worlde) may be trulie, and sincerely rauished with the loue of God, and of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neighbour.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:177048:30"/>
               <p>And therefore as <hi>Origen</hi> excellentlie obserueth in his commentarie vppon <hi>S. Mathewe</hi> his 8. Homilie, vppon those woords of our Sauiour, giuen by waye of <hi>Counsaile</hi> to the youngmanne: <hi>if thou wilt be perfit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Non sic debemus intelligere, vt in eo ipso tempore, quo homo dat bona sua pauperibus, efficiatur omnino perfectus, sed incipit ex eo tempore speculatio Dei adducere eum ad omnes virtutes, vt incipiat ex eo tempore proficere:</hi> that is to say; we are not so to vnderstand perfection, that in the verie moment, wherein a man giueth all his goods to the poore, he is made altogether perfitt, but from that time forwards, the speculatiō of God beginneth to leade him vnto all vertues, that euer after he maketh a good progresse.</p>
               <p>This also is euident in the wordes of our Sauiour, where he placeth not perfection <hi>in ipsa diuitiarum abdicatione,</hi> in the verie renouncing of riches, but rather teacheth, that the forsaking of the worlde is a certaine direction, preparation, or disposition vnto perfection. And so the verie forme, and manner of Christ his speache doth euidentlie conuince. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For first he proposeth the question to his arbitrarie ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>If thou wilt be perfit.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he pursueth it with a direction: <hi>goe sell all that thou hast, and giue to the poore.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, he inferreth the conclusion, the verie life, and consummation of perfection; <hi>followe me.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Lastlie he annexeth the remuneratiō, the forciblest motiue that possible coulde be to drawe a man to that resolution of Christian perfection; <hi>thesaurum habebis in coelo,</hi> thou shalt not want thy rewarde.</p>
               <p>Now this followinge of Christe (which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge els but the soules spirituall vnion with God) is our Christian perfection: wherevnto the abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of riches fitteth, and prepareth a man, listening
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177048:30"/> not so muche to that which is lawfull, as to that which is expedient: auoydinge riches, and other things of like nature, not as things vnlawfull, but as impediments, and hinderances vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes.</p>
               <p>And <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> in his <hi>Enchiridion ad Laurentium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 121.</note> is of opinion, that perfection of charitie (which is the perfection of Christian life) consisteth neither in the sole performaunce of the actions of <hi>precepts,</hi> conformable to <hi>non moechaberis:</hi> nor yet in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmance of the actions of <hi>Counsailes,</hi> vnlesse both actions of <hi>precepts,</hi> and <hi>Counsayles,</hi> be rightlie referred with relatiō to the ende, of all the actions of <hi>precepts</hi> and <hi>Counsailes,</hi> which is <hi>charitas erga Deum, &amp; proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum propter Deum:</hi> charitie toward God primarily, and charitie towards our neighbour for gods sake, secondarily.</p>
               <p>And because the performance of the actions of <hi>precepts,</hi> are, in themselues, absolutely necessarie for atcheiuing this ende (being suche, as without it, the ende cannot be attayned) and the performance of the other of <hi>Counsailes</hi> doth onlie secondarily tende thervnro, as a helpe, or as a <hi>remouens impedimentum:</hi> hence is it that schoole-diuines, haue this distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or rather conclusion comprised in a distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: viz. <hi>Perfection of charitie, which is the perfection of Christian life, consisteth</hi> PRIMARIO, ET ESSEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIALITER IN PRECEPTIS; but SECVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DARIO, ET ACCIDENTALITER IN CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SILIIS; primarily, and essentially in precepts; but seeondarily, and accidentally in Counsayles.</p>
               <p>If anie be so wedded to his owne priuate hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, as not, in this sense,<note place="margin">Benefield, &amp; his confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinians he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy.</note> to admit of Euangelicall Counsailes of perfection, <hi>quoad viam,</hi> and <hi>quoad
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177048:31"/> gradum,</hi> but that they will confounde Precepts, and Counsailes together (houlding both of like necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Counsailes aswell as precepts) so did the hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques called <hi>Apostolici:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">August. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: 40. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane haeres 61.</note> or that Counsailes containe in them no kinde of perfection; it is a braunche of <hi>Iouinian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vigilantius</hi> their cōdemned heresie. Reade <hi>S. Hierom</hi> against <hi>Iouinian;</hi> and <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> in the 10. booke of his Epistles, the 80. and 81. Epistles. Or lastlie, if any will hold the profession of them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, &amp; that there be none; the first crosseth many pregnant testimonies of scriptures veritie; and the secōd thwarteth the ioynt consent of al orthodoxe Antiquitie. The which <hi>Tertullian de praescriptionibus aduersus haereticos; Cyprian de vnitate Ecclesiae: Augustine de vtilitate credendi; Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> in his <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitorium</hi> against all the prophane innouation of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques of his time, make to be the verie square of propheticall, &amp; Apostolicall interpretation, drawne a longe by the line of the Churche.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Principally Benefild.</note>And therefore first; I would but aske them, what our blessed Sauiour meant, <hi>Matth the</hi> 19. (who vppon occasion of the diuorce, his disciples per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, the difficultie of chastitie, exemplified by Eunuches so borne, so made, so making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; <hi>à natura; à violentia; à voluntate,</hi> naturallie, violentlie, voluntarilie; as <hi>Aquinas</hi> well obserueth vppon the place) I say, what meant our Sauiour to propose, <hi>qui potest capere, capiat,</hi> if ther be no COVNSAILE of virginity? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly; I would demaund; what Christ meant, <hi>Matthew the</hi> 19. to aduise the younge man (and that in a matter of the greatest moment; euen the saluation of his soule) <hi>goe sell all that thou hast, and giue to the poore, and thou shalt haue treasure in heauen,</hi> &amp;c. If
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177048:31"/> here be not a <hi>Counsaile</hi> of voluntarie pouertie? For as trulie as Christ meant to performe his promise in the remuneration, <hi>thesaurum habebis in coelo;</hi> so was it vppon condition, that the younge man should embrace that Counsaile of voluntarie pouertie, tending to the toppe of Christian perfection.</p>
               <p>Did Christe, in this, discouer the younge manne his hypocrisie? Some interpreters say so:<note place="margin">Caluin. Marke. 10.22.</note> but <hi>S. Marke</hi> saith no. For Christe looked vppon him, and he <hi>loued</hi> him. It was not (I hope) for his hypocriticall profession and vaine ostentation; but for some good performance, disposition, and inclination. Agayn; Christ had erroneouslie taught him the way to life, by <hi>vade, &amp; vende omnia,</hi> and that this was that one thinge necessarie to aspire to the toppe of Christian perfection, if here be not a <hi>Counsaile</hi> of voluntary pouertie. And this is no lesse then open blasphemie against the Maiestie of heauen.<note place="margin">Caluin is a blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Lastlie I would but demaund, what S. Paul meant 2. Cor. 7.25. to distinguish plainelie betwixt <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Counsailes,</hi> thus; <hi>praeceptum non habeo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">vid. Damasc. dict Gnomi in Indice.</note>
                  <hi>consilium do</hi> (for so the vulgar readeth; which all the latine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurche followeth: and all the greeke fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue soe taken it) if there be no Counsailes? For he groundeth this his distinction vppon his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters wordes; <hi>Non omnes capiunt,</hi> and therfore <hi>S. Paul</hi> had noe precept. But <hi>qui potest capere, capiat.</hi> And hence floweth the secōd branch; <hi>consilium do:</hi> as <hi>S. Hierom, S. Basill,</hi> &amp; diuers others of both Churches do obserue.</p>
               <p>And that this point may be euerie way full, and perfit, builded vppon so manie seuerall rockes, as there be seuerall places of Scriptures:<note place="margin">Vincentius Lyrin. in cō<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> monitorio.</note> let the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Churche speake, being the most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177048:32"/> Maisters &amp; teachers in the Church: &amp;, against <hi>quot capita, tot sensus</hi> (the verie bane of all religion and mother of innouation) let the Churche inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture; and <hi>he that will not heare the Churche,</hi> you knowe what followeth; <hi>sit tibi tanquam hereticus?</hi> Nay; <hi>sit tibi tanquam ethnicus.</hi> For as it is saide of the <hi>letter</hi> of the scripture, that it is not of anie priuate inspiration (For <hi>it came not in ould time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Peter. 1. vlt.</note>
                  <hi>by the will of man, but holie men spake as they were moued by the holie ghost.</hi>) So may it be as trulie saide of the <hi>sense</hi> of the Scripture, that it is not of anie priuate spiritts interpretation. And the reason, why euerie man should fly from a priuate spirits interpretation, is this (as it is excellentlie rendred by that melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Father,<note place="margin">Serm. 17. in Cantic.</note>
                  <hi>S. Bernard) Nonnulli adesse putant spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, cùm non adest, suúmque sensum pro sensu spiritus sequuntur deuiantes, suásque sententias magistrorum senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs praeferunt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A sentence that striketh the Religion in England as dead, as a doore nayle</note> that is (for I cannot but translate it) manie men thinke that they haue the Spirit of God, when they haue it not: erroneouslie followinge the sense of their owne priuate spirits for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the holie Ghost: preferring their owne priuate opinions before the publique iudgmentes of ther maisters, and teachers.</p>
               <p>It is lawfull to follow the spirit in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge the scripture: but it must be the spirit of the Church: that spirit of peace, vnitie, charitie, that descended vppon the Apostles vnited, for <hi>domus vna,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they abode all in one house;</hi> a signe of externall charitie; <hi>Mens, &amp; anima vna;</hi> one minde, one soule; for they had but one God, one faithe, one Churche; a signe of internall,<note place="margin">Ancient Church. Caluins, and Luthers con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregations.</note> spirituall vnitie. The same spirit euer since continued in the Churche, vnited in faithe, not diuided in faction. And wee may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177048:32"/> seeke for the sense of the scripture: but where? It must not be out of the stinkinge puddle of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate braine;<note place="margin">The afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp;c.</note> but forthe of the treasuring me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of the Churche. <hi>Christi Euangelio vim non inferat humana praesumptio: patrum semel definita non sunt iterum in dubium vocanda:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Luther.</note> it is blessed Leo in his 94. Epistle: let not humane presumption dare to offer violence vnto the gospell of Christe: for the constitutions of fathers, once decreed, are not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be questioned. <hi>Nec definitiones eorum perpetuae commutandae, quorum regulam secundum scripturam esse didicimus.</hi> (So speaketh <hi>Flauianus</hi> bishoppe of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople</hi> in his Epistle to Pope LEO the firste) Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the perpetuall determinations of them to be chaunged, whose rule wee haue learned to agree with scripture.</p>
               <p>And therfore to exemplifie further vppon this grounde, and to raise the particuler building vppon this generall foundation: I would but aske; what meant S. Cyprian (that auncient famous martyr, in his tract <hi>de Natiuitate Christi.</hi> sectione 10 penultima) and <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> (that woorthy pillar of the <hi>latine</hi> Churche) in his 26. booke on Iob to stile these <hi>consilia pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fectionis,</hi> Counsailes of perfection, if there be no Counsailes? Secondly; what meant <hi>Theodoret. Primasius, Sedulius, Haymo, Theophylact, Ambrose, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine, Hierome, Gregorie, Basill, Chrysostome, Beda, Lyra, Aquinas, Anselmus,</hi> with all antiquitie <hi>greeke</hi> and latine Churche, so to expounde that place of <hi>S. Paul</hi> 1. Cor. 7.25.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie; what meant <hi>S. Hierome ad Eustochium,</hi> and against that Epicurean Heretique <hi>Iouinian</hi> (one of the first impugners of this Doctrine) <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose in the tenth booke of his Epistles, the</hi> 82. <hi>ad Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellensem
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177048:33"/> Ecclesiam,</hi> and in his tract <hi>de viduis propè finem: S. Augustine</hi> in his 61. sermon <hi>de tempore,</hi> his 18. tracte <hi>de verbis Apostoli,</hi> chapter the 21. his 2. booke of <hi>Euangelicall questions,</hi> chapter the 19. and in his <hi>Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridion ad Laurentium,</hi> chapter 121. <hi>Origen</hi> vppon the 15. to the Rom. <hi>S. Basill de vera virginitate: S. Chrysostome</hi> in his 8. Homilie <hi>de poenitentia: Nazianzen</hi> in his 3. oration (which is the first inuectiue against <hi>Iulian</hi>) and many others? The time would faile me, if I should reckon vppe all. And therfore to close vppe all in a word; What meant all antiquitie, <hi>greeke,</hi> and <hi>latine</hi> fathers, so to distinguishe betwixt precepts, and Counsailes, if ther be no Counsailes.</p>
               <p>To theis I might add Wickliffe against the order of begging friers: where he stileth them <hi>Christ hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> highe</hi> COVNSAYLES. Likewise <hi>Luther</hi> in the 30. article of his assertions. Iudicious &amp; learned <hi>Hooke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in his Churche Politie, and the Apologie in defence of him in the chapter of satisfaction. The Bishoppe of <hi>Rochester</hi> (and elect of <hi>Lincolne</hi>) in his sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at court cōcerning the authoritie of Bishopps;<note place="margin">D. Barlovv.</note> the 4. page, before the ende.</p>
               <p>These, and manie more of their ranke I might adde; if I could be persuaded, that the Fathers nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their sonns suffrages.<note place="margin">Sonnes in this poynt; or such like. For no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervvayes did I meane.</note> And yet certaine I am, that the sonns stande in neede of their fathers testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. Or were it not rather so, that all these (being men of eminent note in our Churche) are rather <hi>relatores antiquae fidei, quàm authores nouae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae;</hi> relators of the auncient faithe of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, (to their credit and honour, in that respect, be it spoken) rather then authours, &amp; coyners of anie newe doctrine? And therfore passing them, and for this time sparing them, not to strike a hairs breadth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177048:33"/> from my former grounds; my maine conclusion is this: <hi>maneant termini patrum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leo Epist. 17. &amp; 94.</note>
                  <hi>intráque fines proprios se quisque contineat: sufficiant limites, quos sanctorum patrum prouidentissima decreta posuerunt:</hi> let the bounds of auncient Churche abide, and let euerie man keepe himselfe within due bounds, and limits; let the meetes which the Fathers most prouident decrees haue set, content vs. And the reason is excellentlie rendred by <hi>S. Bernard:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epist. 77. ad Hugonē de S. Victore.</note> viz. <hi>quantò viciniores erant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entui saluatoris, tantò mysterium salutis pleniùs p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ecepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt:</hi> the nearer the Fathers were to Christ his incarnation, the more clearlie, and fullie receaued they the mysterie of saluation.</p>
               <p>To these, were my iudgment and opinion any, I durst not otherwayes then subscribe with all humble submission to the censure of the Churche; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earinge that censure of <hi>Flauianus</hi> (Bishoppe of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tantinople,</hi>) in his first Epistle to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the first;<note place="margin">Of Luther, Caluin, and all their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per disciples Qui nō con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentit Sācto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Patrum expositioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, seipsum alienat ab omni sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotali com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione, &amp; à Christi praesertia Eudoxius in Cōcil. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note>
                  <hi>Haeretici est praecepta patrum declinare, &amp; instituta eorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>espicere:</hi> It is the propertie of an Heretique to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>line the precepts of holie fathers, contemninge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her cannons, and decrees.</p>
               <p>Thus much be spoaken in defence of that great pillar of the <hi>latine</hi> Churche <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> saying; <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam non iudicantur, &amp; pereunt, quidam iudicantur, &amp; pereunt; quidam iudicantur, &amp; regnant, quidam non iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantur, &amp; regnant:</hi> as also in defence of that sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, inferred vppon the last braunche, <hi>transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt aliqui praecepta legis perfectiori virtute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I haue the rather done (God, and his holie Angells in whose presence I nowe stande, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peake, bearinge me witnesse) lest that imputation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Fulgentius</hi> should light vppon me;<note place="margin">De Mysterio Mediatoris lib. 1.</note> viz. <hi>Fidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cclesiae nolle asserere, est negare, vno eodémque silentio
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177048:34"/> firma errorem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">As hereticks as tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers.</note>
                  <hi>qui errore, seu tempore possessus, veritatem silendo non astruit; Dominicam gloriam qui non firmârit, euacuat; &amp; diuinam contumeliam qui non refutarit, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulat. Miles ignauus somnolento corpore depressus, regia castra oppugnantibus tradit, dum competentibus vigilijs non defendit.</hi> That is; not to auerre the Doctrine of the Churche, is to denie the faithe of the Churche; for with one, and the selfe same silence, he streing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth an errour,<note place="margin">So are some in England. So are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</note> who being possessed or carried awaye with errour, or time, auoucheth not truthe by his silence. He that confirmeth not the glorie of God, weakneth it; and he that confuteth not iniurie offred vnto God, augmenteth it. The sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sleepie souldier betrayeth the Kings tents to his enimies, whilst he keepeth not true sentinell as he shoulde.</p>
               <p>Hath anie weedes of superstitiō growne vpp with this Doctrine in the feilde of the Churche? Oh le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the pure wheate of <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection <hi>quoad viam, quoad gradum,</hi> fare the wors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the weedes. Vnskilfull husbandmen are they &amp; verie vnfit to manure, the Lord his tillage, whose preposterous zeale issuing from the grounde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> priuate groundles iudgment, would pull vppe bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wheate, and tares together.</p>
               <p>These are wiser, and fuller of zeale, then Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himself, who suffred, nay gaue commaundement (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is in the parable) that both <hi>tares and wheate shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> growe together,</hi> vntill the haruest of the last iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment; and then should the tares, and weedes b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bounde vppe in bundles, fitted for the fire; and the wheate should be gathered in to his barne. For a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the last iudgment,<note place="margin">sermo. 3. de Ieiunio &amp; collectis.</note> ther are somethings <hi>vrenda flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> other things <hi>condenda horreis,</hi> as S. LEO speaketh
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177048:34"/> And doth not <hi>S. Paul</hi> allude to this?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12.23.</note> Whose woordes be; <hi>if anie man builde vppon Christ (the foundation) gould, siluer, pretious stones, timber, haye, stubble; euery mans woorke shalbe made manifest, for the day shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, because it shalbe reuealed by the fire, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re shall trie euerie mans woorkes, of what sorte they are.</hi> To which fire, let this Doctrine be reserued to stand, or fall; to burne as stubble, hay, timber; or rather to escape, as goulde, siluer, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious stones.</p>
               <p>Now to God onlie wise be rendred prayse, power, might, maiestie, rule, dominion, and thanksgiuinge, and let all the creatures in heauen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n earthe, or vnder the earthe, say <hi>so be it; Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> A Conclusion of the <hi>FIRST PART;</hi> vvith an admonition vnto the Academicall Reader.</head>
               <p>THVS (gentle Reader) thou hast seene my mayne defence of this doctrine, wherein I haue followed the mature aduise of the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher,</hi> and Oratour.<note place="margin">Arist. in To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picis Cicero ad Heren.</note> For I thought it not suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to confirme truth in the former part of this sermon, vnlesse I confuted falsehood also in the later. And this I did for establishing thee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177048:35"/> if thou be in the right: or reducing thee vnto it, if thou hast bene in the wronge.</p>
               <p>And howsoeuer the truth of this doctrine hath not allready (nor yet haply herafter shall) escape the tongues, and penns of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or ignorant carping aduersaries) enimies of God, and his Church) yet can it neuer be suppressed; but it will preuayle in the end, and florish like a greene palmetree; being iustifiable and glorious both before God, &amp; man where reason swayeth, and not passion rageth.</p>
               <p>Farther; I can for more full complement (if neede be) produce all charters, roles, euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, iudgments, censures, sentences, arrests of all Christian parliaments, the vmpiring deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the highest Ecclesiasticall tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, &amp; generall Councells notwithstanding all pretenses, pleas, intrusions, surreptions, shifts, cōtentions of all Hereticall <hi>Iouinianists.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such is the difference betwixt truth, and falsehood, that errour in time (as it is but the enterteynement of time) will of it selfe fall away,<note place="margin">Ad nihillum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leuenient tanquā aqua decurrens: vvhich S. Augustine doth f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ly apply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto heresies</note> when TRVTH will stand impregnable, how many soeuer impugne her; so true is that of the Apostle; <hi>vve can do nothing against truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therfore leauing thee (modest, and discrete Reader) to iudge of the matter, and doctrine now in difference, as reason, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion shall induce thee, and not as the instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177048:35"/> &amp; humour of some factious persons will seeke to misleade thee; I proceede to prosecute the remaynder of this businesse; hoping that no man (of any apprehension) will suffer him selfe to be deceaued by vaine, and vnlearned suggestions.</p>
               <p>And if some men will obstinately shutt their eyes, yet my trust is, that others will looke vp to Heauen, whence this doctrine descended, and whither it doth most readily conduce; &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they will no longer take darkenesse for light, night for day, poyson for medecine, Heresy for verity; since truth bringeth euer with it, certainty, peace, &amp; security at the last.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177048:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:177048:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177048:37"/>
            <argument>
               <p>THE SECOND PART Contayning the irregular, &amp; violent processe of the Vicechancellour, &amp; hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> complices against me, and the former doctrine. Ʋvherein the Reader may excellently discerne the nature of heresy, and the condition of Hereticks, as in a perfitt glasse.</p>
            </argument>
            <epigraph>
               <q>As <hi>Iannes,</hi> and <hi>Mambres</hi> resisted <hi>Moses,</hi> so do theis resist the truth; men corrupt in mynd, &amp; reprobate concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the faith. <bibl>2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:177048:37"/>
            <head>A TRIVMPH OF TRVTH. OR DECLARATION OF THE DOCTRINE CONCERNING EVANGELICALL COVNSAYLES;</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Hovv <hi>D. HVTTON</hi> conuented me vpon the deliuery of the last Sermon; and vvhat occurrents passed at that time.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had ended my sermon, it seemed good vnto M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Hutton</hi> (who was there present, and confronted me with ridiculous behauiour) to cite me before him selfe immediately in his owne lodging; where I found him accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with two other Doctours; <hi>D. Kilby,</hi> and <hi>D. Benefield,</hi> who gaue speciall attention vnto my sermon, with great shew of discontent.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:177048:38"/>
               <p>Before these men, <hi>D. Hutton</hi> beganne to chardge me with <hi>scandalous, erroneous,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> doctrine, fitter to be preached in <hi>Rome,</hi> then in <hi>Oxford;</hi> and therefore, in no case to be suffred there to disturbe the peace of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity.</p>
               <p>To this accusation, I framed my answeare to the same tenour, and effect, as you haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly seene in the <hi>kitchin-conference;</hi> adding farther, that the doctrine of the <hi>Trinity, consub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiality</hi> &amp;c. might be branded with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of POPERY, aswell as this doctrine of EVANGELICALL COVNSAILES.</p>
               <p>But such is the temerity of some men, that they will rather disclayme a manifest truthe, then they will concurre in opinion with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And for my part, I see no reason, why you may not aswell renounce that <hi>Popish</hi> doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as this of <hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Counsayles,</hi> since both haue their eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence from the same ground (<hi>Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticall Tradition</hi>) yea the later hath more cleare deduction, and testification out of the Scripture then the former.</p>
               <p>Secondly; his worshippe obiected vnto me that <hi>D. Benefield</hi> had lately; and learnedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed the said <hi>Popish</hi> doctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles,</hi> and that therevpon I ought to haue surceased; my reply was, that <hi>D. Benefield</hi> his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177048:38"/> opinion was no canon of my faith, nor that his authority was of such value with me, as to preponderate the iudgment of the Ancient Church, &amp; testimonies of the venerable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And therefore since I beganne to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishe this doctrine vppon such groundes, I was bound in conscience to defend the same; and specially, since he made an opposition in schooles vnto my position in the pulpit; so that I could not be silent without treason vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and his truth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; whereas he laid vnto my chardge, that he had inhibited me to intermeddle any farther with this point; I answered; rhat <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> he had neuer done it, and that, <hi>de iure,</hi> he could not do it. For <hi>God must be obayed rather then man.</hi> Besides; though in discretion,<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> and submissiō vnto your authoritie, I would haue surceased from prosecution of this matter, yet this notorious, &amp; intollerable impugnatiō did force me to breake my intended silence.</p>
               <p>Fourthly; whereas he demaunded a copy of my sermon (protesting vpon his <hi>faith, &amp; troth to God,</hi> that he would send me presently vnto the Castle, vnlesse I then deliuered it) I was content (vpon the perswasion of <hi>D. Kilbye</hi>) to yealde into his handes the original, and onely copy therof. And so I was dismissed for this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:177048:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Hovv the Vicechancellour, after his returne from <hi>London,</hi> intreated me in his lodging.</head>
               <p>THIS storme being thus ouerblowne, a quiet calme ensued, vntill M. Doctour <hi>King</hi> (deane of <hi>Christ-Church,</hi> and <hi>Vicechancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> of the vniuersity) was now returned from <hi>London;</hi> vnto whom I made repayre, partly to do my duty vnto him, &amp; partly to preuent that sinister impression, which D. <hi>Hutton,</hi> &amp; others sought to worke in him to the preiudice of me and of the doctrine which I had preached. For which purpose, I had collected the testimonies of 24. <hi>Fathers;</hi> that therby he might be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the state of this present question.</p>
               <p>As soone as he beheld me, he brake foorth into this passionate declamation. <hi>Sir, would you haue a vvord vvith me? In very good time; I haue many vvords to speake with you: for the shameful ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of your doctrine hath filled my eares wheresoeuer I came, in London, in Lambeth, or else where: your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was still laid in my dish; yea I haue bene chard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by diuers to my face, for tolerating such scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and erroneous doctrine freely, and openly to be preached in this vniuersity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To whom returning my answere in dutifull
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177048:39"/> sort, I protested first, that I came not to insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate with him, nor to diuert any course of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice. Secōdly; I know the doctrine to be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon such inuincible proofes, &amp; reasons, that it will stād impregnable against al assaults whatsoeuer. For demonstration wherof I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented the aforesaid testimonies vnto him, and desired him to take a diligent reuiew of the places alleaged in that schedule.</p>
               <p>Vvherevpon he contēptuously entwited me, saying: <hi>go, go; you are a foole, an asse &amp;c. vvhen you preach, here is nothing but Leo, Leech, and all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> A prouerbe, which he had borrowed frō some braynsick <hi>Puritans,</hi> &amp; prophane scoffers.</p>
               <p>VVhich contumely I repelled with few words, and digested it with patience; assuring him, that <hi>Leech</hi> with one LEO would be too hard for any man that impugned this doctrine.</p>
               <p>And truly I could not but maruaile, that he, who in his lectures vpon <hi>Ionah,</hi> hath made a copious defence of the holy <hi>Fathers,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth the vse of their testimonies in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que sermōs, should now so vehemently except against me, and so meanely esteeme of them. But such is the condition of these men, that they will accept, and reiect the <hi>Fathers</hi> at their owne pleasures; as winde, and weather go.</p>
               <p>Now, whereas I added farther, that the best learned in <hi>Oxford</hi> concurred with me in this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177048:40"/> point; <hi>yea</hi> (said he) <hi>there are many of you, that vvill play vvith</hi> POPERY, <hi>as the flye doth vvith the candle: you hoouer, ouer and about it, as neere as you dare, but you vvill be sure to keepe your vvinges from sindging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though I made a freindly defence of those men (at whom he malitiously gyrded) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of incomparable worth in that place, yet I disclaymed al assistance from them, or any others, protesting, that I depended not vpon men, nor Angells; but only vpon the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, interpreted by the ancient Church. VVhich rule of faith as it is most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, so my application therof, in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, is free from all exception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVell</hi> (quoth he) <hi>vvhether I shall be able to prooue this doctrine, false, or not, I can not tell: but, as I thinke, I shall. Hovvsoeuer; certaine I am, that I shall be able to condemne you of great indiscretion, for preaching such doctrine in these reuolting times, vvhen there is such generall Apostasy from the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell vnto</hi> POPERY.</p>
               <p>At which simple suggestion I could not but smile within my selfe; first to consider, that whereas he had absolutely charged this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be <hi>erroneous,</hi> yet now he could not tell whether it were <hi>true,</hi> or <hi>false.</hi> Secondly, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue, that the preaching of truth, contayned in the gospell, should be a meanes to draw
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177048:40"/> men from the gospell vnto <hi>Popery;</hi> as he was pleased to speake.</p>
               <p>But perceiuing him to be enkindled with the flames of passion, I forboare to adde fuel vnto the fire; and therefore I pretermitted the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of his follies at that time. Onely I made this breife answere: that if some truth be not to be preached at all times, yet the CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRARY vnto truth was to be preached at no time: and if it be lawfull for any man to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it, is it not lawfull for me to defend, it and especially, when it concerneth my selfe in particular? For so it did in this case: the eye of the whole <hi>vniuersity</hi> being cast vpon me in this behalfe.</p>
               <p>Thus I tooke my leaue of <hi>M. Vicechancellour,</hi> he being full of passion and I of resolution for this matter: against which he declamed with many words, and without any reason; consor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting herin with those furious <hi>Donatists,</hi> of whō <hi>S. Augustine</hi> pronounceth truly:<note place="margin">Contra lit. Petil. l. 2. c. 51.</note>
                  <hi>Quid hoc aliud es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, quàm nescire quid dicere, &amp; tamen non posse nisi maledicere?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The finall proceedings of <hi>D. King,</hi> and his assistents against me, and my doctrine.</head>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:177048:41"/>
               <p>THIS Magistrate intending a preposte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous course against me, &amp; yet pretending a formality of iustice, conuented me before him in iuridicall manner, vpon the vigill of S. PETER, a practitioner of my doctrine. <hi>Lord</hi> (said he) <hi>vvhat shall vve haue, that haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken all, and follovved thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours (of better vvorth) vvho heard my Sermons vvere not called vnto my triall; vvhereas 2 onely of these six Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges vvere my Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</note>Appearing now vpon my summons, I found M. <hi>vicechancellour</hi> assisted with 5. compeeres; <hi>D. Airay, D. Aglionbee, D. Hutton, D. Harding, D. Benefield;</hi> a selected company for his owne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. VVho as they were generally to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted against by me, as incompetent Iudges: so in special <hi>D. Hutton</hi> for his inueterate malice conceiued against me longe since vpon a base, &amp; vnworthy respect. <hi>D. Benefield,</hi> as he was my principal opposite,<note place="margin">Quid mihi dabis. &amp;c.</note> so he, with the rest, being a doctrinall <hi>Caluinist</hi> could neuer afford me an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall triall in this issue, depēding vpon the FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERS; which he, &amp; they, do really disclayme.</p>
               <p>These petty Iudges being thus assembled; M. <hi>vicechancellour</hi> inueighed against me with a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; passionate speach, contayning in it these capitall accusations. First; that I had lately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ached <hi>scandalous,</hi> &amp; <hi>erroneous</hi> Doctrine. Secōd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that I was vehemently suspected of POPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY, &amp; that, by this doctrine, I had now iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the suspition. Thirdly; that I had brought an infamy vpon the vniuersity, and in speciall
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177048:41"/> vpon him, and his house. VVherfore I must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a censure according to my demerit.</p>
               <p>To the first I answered, that as vpon sufficient discouery of the pretended <hi>errour,</hi> I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant it (since I sought nothing but the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of truth) so I should consequently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that I had giuen the scandall if I haue preached the errour. But my conscience telleth me, that I haue offended neither in matter, nor manner; substance, nor circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</p>
               <p>To the second; that men might suspect what they pleased, &amp; that it lay not in me to hinder euery supition. As for the imputation of <hi>Popery</hi> in this point, it cleaueth vnto the Scripture, &amp; all Antiquity from which (ioyntly) I assumed this <hi>Popish</hi> doctrine.</p>
               <p>To the third; that as he, and his house could receiue no infamy by such a truth, so much lesse the <hi>vniuersity;</hi> forasmuch as the best in iudgment there, (if not the most in number also) concurred with me in this point.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>D. Aglionbee</hi> suddainly interrupted me; demaunding, who they were; and, making me the trumpetter onely of other mens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he said, that I was set on by some, who, though they affected this, and other such like points of <hi>Popery,</hi> yet they dare not broach them themselues, but whosoeuer they are, they shall
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177048:42"/> be mett with all either in schooles, or pulpit.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Miles gloriosus,</hi> who challendgeth his betters for POPERY;<note place="margin">At Metton Coll. before a great as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly.</note> but they are able, and will confidently appeach him, not only of <hi>Iouinian</hi> heresy (which he defended expressely against <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) but of sondry other <hi>blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> &amp; <hi>Heresies,</hi> which he preached publikely in <hi>S. Maries</hi> Churche: the particulars whereof I haue seene in wryting.</p>
               <p>These things I could haue then obiected vnto him. But being not willing now to exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate him, or any other there present, I retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him my answere in this manner. Sir; it may suffice you now to vnderstand, that there are such men in this vniuersity, that wil constantly defend this doctrine: who they are, I leaue it vnto your inquiry; you may finde them out by getting a generall subscription here vnto your opinion, or by some other meanes. Onely, to giue you farther assurance of there resolution in this point, it pleased some of them freely (without my desire or knowledge) to draw a letter, wherin they recommended me, and my cause vnto the Archbishopp of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming his Grace, that the doctrine was most cleare on my side, and that they would stand in publick iustification therof.</p>
               <p>But I pray you, Sir. to be aduertised by me; that I neuer made vse of their letters: one
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177048:42"/> reason wherof meeteth with your obiection. For as I assumed this doctrine from the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> so I determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to maintaine it vpon these grounds, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any assistance: and much lesse was <hi>I set on by any of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that you may know vpon what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity I first beganne, and do now procede; here are the Doctours (24 in number 12. <hi>Greeke</hi> 12. <hi>Latine</hi>) who <hi>set me on;</hi> here are their testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; produce their bookes; conuince me if you can.</p>
               <p>VVhereat his courage beganne to abate; &amp; first he excepted against me for producing the <hi>Greeke,</hi> in whose language (said he) you haue but slender skill.</p>
               <p>To which malitious, and impertinent excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I answered first; that it was sufficient for me to rely vpon the <hi>translations</hi> approued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in the Church. Secondly;<note place="margin">Do not many Deui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland, and the people generally rely vpon the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures vvhose originall they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not?</note> that I had so much skill in <hi>Greeke,</hi> as to compare the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the originall, and that none there was so exact, as to vnderstand some <hi>Greeke</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (&amp; namely <hi>S. Gregory Nazianzen</hi>) in their natiue idiome. Thirdly; that if I had no <hi>Greeke</hi> Authour on my side; yet here is a sufficient Iurie of <hi>Latine</hi> Fathers, whose language I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, &amp; whose conspiring tenent, I hope, you dare not renounce.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:177048:43"/>
               <p>Doctour <hi>Aglionbee</hi> being thus pressed by me &amp; hauing nothing to answere in his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; <hi>D King</hi> interposed himselfe; obiecting that <hi>D. Hutton</hi> had inhibited me: that <hi>D. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> (whose bookes I was not worthy to cary) had publiquely confuted my doctrine &amp;c. whith such like friuolous allegations.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>D. Hutton</hi> his inhibition I answered as before; adding farther that I respected not his iudgment in this matter. For I knew (indeede) that as his vnderstanding is not very deepe, so his affection is not very good; who, in a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne booke (or rather statizing pamphlet) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>crosse in baptisme;</hi> defēdeth this lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Christian ceremonie by tradition of the Church, as it is witnessed by the holy Fathers: and yet now in a point of greater importance, expressed in scripture, taught by Fathers, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised by the Saints, defined by the whole Church, he blushed not to accuse me, nay S. GREGORY himself of <hi>Popery</hi> in this doctrine. But singular is my comfort to consider, by what <hi>Iudge,</hi> I am thus vsed, in what <hi>cause,</hi> and with what <hi>Patrone;</hi> from whom our Nation first receiued her first faith, &amp; for whose faith I must now forsake my nation.</p>
               <p>As for D. <hi>Benefeild</hi> with his lecture, and his bookes, I passed them ouer: considering that M. Vicechācellour made excursions from the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177048:43"/> point, loading me only with contumely and disgrace.</p>
               <p>VVherfore, not suffering him to diuert me from the mayne issue, I desired him to deale punctually, that is to say, first to admitt a triall by the Fathers, or to deny it: if he denyed it, he should be therby sufficiently conuinced. Secōdly; if he admitted this trial,<note place="margin">Haeretici est praecepta Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare; saith vvorthy Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian in his first epist to LEO the Great.</note> then either to disprooue my authorities, or to approoue my doctrine.</p>
               <p>But he not daring to make a briefe, &amp; pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall answere to my reasonable demaundes, fell extrauagantly into a mention of the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches;</hi> summoning me before their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall, for the censuring of this doctrine.</p>
               <p>VVhich course of proceeding, I vtterly disclaymed, as vnequall; because the later Church is not to iudge the former, but cōtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the former is to iudge the later.</p>
               <p>And what did I herein (good Reader) but obserue the prescription of Antiquity in this behalfe,<note place="margin">Cōtra Iulian Pelag. lib. 1.</note> &amp; namely that of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> against the <hi>Pelagian</hi> hereticks; PATRES <hi>oportet vt populi Christiani vestris nouitatibus anteponāt, eis{que} potius eligant adhaerere, quàm vobis?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>D. Airay</hi> distasting my refusall to stand vnto the verdict of the <hi>reformed Churches,</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned with me about the rule of my faith; I answered him breifly; that I wholly followed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177048:44"/>
                  <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> his direction;<note place="margin">Cōtra haeref cap. 1. &amp;c See D. Field. pag. 239.</note> to witt, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall scripture,</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticall tradition;</hi> the first being sensed by the second.</p>
               <p>This rule he called <hi>Popish,</hi> exclayming against it as the very ground of <hi>Popery,</hi> &amp; superstition. VVhereupon I desired him (for my better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction) to giue a rule of faith more certaine, &amp; infallible then this, which he branded with such disgracefull imputation.</p>
               <p>VVhy (said he) <hi>vvhat other ground of faith, then the pure vvord of God?</hi> I demaunded then; who shall interpret this word? He replyed; <hi>the spirit.</hi> Vvhat spirit good Sir? <hi>The spirit of God</hi> only which priuate men thinke they haue? Against which rule I excepte, for that it was the common plea of all condemned Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques. Vvherefore I required a triall of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended spirit; for I can not admitt that to be God his spirit in any priuate man, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senteth not with the spirit of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church. And thus you see M. D. Airay that what you formerly reiected out of my rule, as <hi>Popish,</hi> you must necessarily admit as true; that is: <hi>Ecclesiasticall Tradition</hi> annexed to the <hi>sacred Canon</hi> for the discerning of priuate spirits. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes each Heretique will sense scripture in the mould of his owne brayne.</p>
               <p>And now M. <hi>D. Airay</hi> being thus ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in the rule of his faith, proposed vnto
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177048:44"/> me a question of capitall daunger; wishing M. <hi>Vicechancellour</hi> to question me vpon the poynt of the kings SVPREMACY; for surely (said he) you shall find him vnsound therin.</p>
               <p>But M. <hi>Vicechancellours</hi> thoughts caried him so farre away at that present, that he gaue no eare vnto this impertinēt, &amp; bloudy question: but prosecuting the vindictiue designement (formerly cōcluded vpon betwixt <hi>D. Aglionbee,</hi> &amp; himselfe who held a secret conference toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) he resumed his old accusations of <hi>false, erroneous, scandalous,</hi> and <hi>Popish</hi> doctrine: for deliuering, and reinforcing whereof, I deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the seuerity of Iustice.</p>
               <p>Perceiuing now their resolution to punish me without farther examination of my cause, or respect of my iust defence, I finally propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto them these two demaunds.</p>
               <p>FIRST; that they would proceede against me iuridically, &amp; by way of <hi>Articles;</hi> so I should know precisely what was the errour, and false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of my Doctrine; and they should receiue my answere made in forme of law. For this hath euer bene the custome of proceding in this vniuersity, and in God his Church.</p>
               <p>Hereunto <hi>M. Vicechancellour</hi> replyed. <hi>VVhat? Articles? you shall haue articles time inough: meane vvhile, I say that all</hi> (meaning my Sermon) <hi>is false; scandalous, Popish, erroneous.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:177048:45"/>
               <p>My SECOND demaund therupon was; that he, and his associates would condescend vnto this small request; to witt; I will here set downe this affirmatiue proposition; SVNT EVANGELICA CONSILIA; &amp; subscribe vnto it in your presence. May it please you also to sett downe the negatiue, NON SVNT EVANGELICA CONSILIA; and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe your seuerall names thereunto; and sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify therewithall, that you haue punished me for teaching the contrary assertion.</p>
               <p>This request, <hi>D. King</hi> not onely denyed, but also exclaymed against me for making this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. And no meruayle; for he that durst ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, throughout this whole proceeding, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, and by expresse mention, condemne <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles;</hi> how could he yeald vnto any such subscription? whereby he and the rest might haue remayned HERETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QVES vpon thiere owne record.</p>
               <p>The conclusion of all was this, <hi>M. Vicechan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour</hi> beating me downe with the blow of authority (hauing no other meanes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince me) pronounced his definitiue sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence against me; which I wil here relate word for word, as neere as I could possibly beare it away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Leech; for preaching scandalous, and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine (Doctrine, as you vvell knovv, stiffly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177048:45"/> defended by the Church of Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He named none, but (as I conceiue) this vvas one: viz The virginall estate excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugall An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thus you may see; Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tis est REX sed fortior Mulier. 3. Esdr. 3.</note>
                  <hi>and vvhereupon many absurdities do follovv) I do first as</hi> VICE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHANCELLOVR <hi>silence you from preaching. Secondly; as</hi> DEANE <hi>of this house, I suspend you from your commons and function here for the space of tvvelue moneths.</hi> This is my sentence; and before these my Associates I require you to take notice thereof.</p>
               <p>Vvhich sentēce though it were tyrannicall &amp; vniust, yet it no wayes discouraged me, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed me in my opinion. wherefore I protested the doctrine againe more resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely, then before; wishing <hi>M. Vicechancellour,</hi> &amp; his assistants to vnderstād thus much from me. First: that I held the doctrine with asmuch, nay more confidence then euer I did. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly: that I farther concluded the inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the point out of the manner of their proceedings, whereat they were driuen into the extremity of furie, and passion.</p>
               <p>Thus the assembly was dissolued, and I, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>M. Vicechancellour</hi> in mind of the <hi>Articles</hi> (which he formerly promised, and bade me now to expect within two, or three dayes) tooke my leaue for that time.</p>
               <p>And now (courteous Reader) since thou hast seene the proceedings of theis men, consider with me,<note place="margin">In ps. Cōtra partem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati.</note> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ether I haue not iust cause to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne against them as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> cōplayned
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177048:46"/> longe before against the <hi>Donatisticall</hi> faction.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erunt quod voluerunt tunc in illâ caecitate:</l>
                  <l>Non Iudices sederunt, non Sacerdotes de more,</l>
                  <l>Quod solent in magnis causis congregati judicare:</l>
                  <l>Non accusator, &amp; reus steterunt in quaestione,</l>
                  <l>Non testes, &amp; documentū: quo possent crimē probare.</l>
                  <l>Sed Furor, Dolus, Tumultus: qui regnant in falsitate.</l>
               </q>
               <p>VVherefore I conclude this whole passadge with the burthen of that excellent psalme:
<q>Omnes qui gaudetis de pace, modò <hi>VERVM</hi> judicate.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Hovv <hi>D. King</hi> dealt injuriously vvith me, and perfidiously, concerning the <hi>AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICLES</hi> vvhich should expresse some crimes particularly obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted against me.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 25.27.</note>VVHEN <hi>S. Paul</hi> had appealed vnto the tribunall of CAESAR: <hi>Festus</hi> (the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty) thought it <hi>an vnreasonable thing to send a prisoner vnto his Lord, and not to signify the cause.</hi> For thus the light of nature could teach an Heathen, that, in discretion, and in iustice no man should be called into question, without a pretense (at the least) of some speciall crime.</p>
               <p>But see now a Christian Magistrate inferiour
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177048:46"/> vnto an heathen in his behalfe: who did not onely conuent, but condemne me: and neuer signified <hi>the cause:</hi> which yet could be none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then that which concerned <hi>S. Paul him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe:</hi> CONSILIVM DO &amp;c.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit, if he had dealt with me according to the law of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (an heathen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) &amp; had tried my cause equally,<note place="margin">Boem. de mor. gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> after he had inflickted punishment vpon my person, yet then also there had bene some shew of iustice in his proceedings.</p>
               <p>But see now farther, how he is inferiour vnto heathens in this respect: nay yet more: how he added perjury vnto his iniustice. For whereas he promised to deliuer ARTICLES vnto me, which should containe (precisely) the <hi>cause</hi> of his former seuere sentēce against me, yet when (according to his owne appointement) I came vnto him personally to require them, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied absolutely that he had euer made any such promise. And when I pressed him more particularly thereunto, adding al circūstances (of time, place, persons &amp;c.) so that he could not haue any semblable euasion, he desperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forsware himselfe: saying (with many inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations) VPON MY FAITH,<note place="margin">Fides Puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note>
                  <hi>I neuer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised you any</hi> ARTICLES; <hi>you belie me.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>VVhen I perceiued what small conscience he made either of faith in his promise, or of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177048:47"/> equity in his proceedings, I desyred him with many earnest obtestations, that it would please him, at the least, to signify vnto me now by word of mouth, expressely what that point is, for which he had thus punished me to my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and losse. And this fauour I humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested at his hands asmuch for the general, as my owne particular satisfactiō. For many saw the punishmēt, but could not know the cause.</p>
               <p>This petition was reinforced in my name by a graue, and ancient M. of Arts; who pleaded to obtaine the same in regard of <hi>Iustice, VVis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> Iustice; because (sayd he) it was the forme of law, that the party accused should answere articulately vnto the crime ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected.<note place="margin">See Act. 25.16 vt accus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus locum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fendendi accipiar ad a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uenda or mina, quae ei obijciun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> Vvisedome; that you may deliuer your selfe from the suspition of iniury; &amp; especially since the whole <hi>Vniuersity</hi> is much distracted vpon these late proceedings. <hi>Charity;</hi> that you may rectify <hi>M. Leech</hi> his vnderstāding by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conuiction of his supposed errour. And I dare promise in his behalf,<note place="margin">To punish vvithout in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, it is tyranny. Salust.</note> that if you can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince his iudgement, he will recant the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; for I haue heard him often protest thus much.</p>
               <p>Theis reasons, and persuasions of my friend, entered so deepely into <hi>M. Doctour Kings</hi> heart for the present, that he promised to conuent me againe, and that he would proceede with
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177048:47"/> me according to my desire herein. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing he violated this promise also to his exceeding great disreputation.</p>
               <p>But I come now vnto his answere, which he made vnto my former humble petition. <hi>Sir.</hi> (said he) <hi>it shall satisfy you, and the vniuersity, that</hi> I HAVE DONE IT; <hi>take your remedy, where you can. If I haue vvronged you heere, right your self elsevvhere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was spoken like a KING deed; and not like a subiect; who though he be a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate ouer others, yet should be subordinate vnto a common Law, and Lord. And happy are those gouermēts, where the wise sentence of an heathen Poet is not neglected.<note place="margin">Horat.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quicquid à vobis minor extimescet,</l>
                  <l>Major hoc vobis Dominus minatur.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This was my last refuge, and finall hope; but how farre I was deceiued in my iust expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the sequele shal declare.<note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Hovv I vvas summoned to <hi>S. Paules</hi> Crosse, and defeated. <hi>D. Kings</hi> conference vvith a learned Doctour in <hi>London,</hi> about <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:177048:48"/>
               <p>BEING now silenced by the <hi>Vicechancellour</hi> from preaching within the precincts of the vniuersity, so that I could not exercise my function neither in the publique audience of the learned, nor yet in any of the parish Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (which I had vsually visited, by course, euery sabboth, and holy day; vnlesse some spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall occasion diuerted me from my customa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practise) I receaued letters from the Lord Bishopp of <hi>London</hi> (my very Honourable, and much respected freind; whom it pleased freely to bestow that place vpon me, in regard of my first sermon preached in <hi>Oxford,</hi> from which his successour had now suspended me for the last) wherein his Lordshipp required me to preache at <hi>S. Paules</hi> crosse, and not to fayle at the time prefixed in his summons. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I prepared my selfe accordingly, &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed his Lordshipp thereof, as he had enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me in his said letters.</p>
               <p>The Vicechancellour, getting notice of these summons, sent for me immediately, and requested that he might haue a view of the Bishoppes Letters; which, in courtesy, I then communicated vnto him, howbeit I had iust reason to suspect (for his countenance expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed much perturbation in his heart) that he would plott some meanes to hinder this desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnement. And as (in all probability) he did
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:177048:48"/> coniecture that I would haue constantly asse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered my former doctrine in the greatest au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diēce of the kingdome, so I must acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that this was my resolued determination.</p>
               <p>But Maister <hi>D. King</hi> fearing least with so publick a promulgation of this truth, I should also blazon his shame (which now neither <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> nor <hi>London,</hi> nor our diuided world it selfe shall containe within hir limitts) handled the matter so by his policy, and authority, that my lord of <hi>London</hi> (through his misinforming suggestions) countermaunded the former by second letters; dischardging me from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that duty. And now Maister Vicechancellour thought that he had not onely inconuenienced me, but also secured himselfe.</p>
               <p>For this end, and purpose also he repayred then vnto a Doctour of principall place, and eminent worth (a man not vnder any; if not ouer all) with whom he intertayned longe dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course touching the Doctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes;</hi> complayning that in <hi>Oxford,</hi> it had bene lately broached, and obstinately defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And now, I pray you, good Sir (said he) <hi>vvhat is your opinion concerning this point?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here by the way, giue me leaue (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to propose two things vnto thy discreete consideration. FIRST; that D. King either
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177048:49"/> had no knowledge at all, or not well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that point, wherein he condemned me by violence of authority, and not by force of reason. SECONDLY; that as I suffred with a <hi>good</hi> cōscience, so he punished me with an <hi>euill.</hi> For I had not the least scruple, nor diffidence in this point. Al testimonies, diuine, humane; of God, and of his Chuch, did firmely esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish me therein. And therfore, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with many learned men vpon the same, yet I neuer demaunded of any man, by way of doubt; Sir. <hi>vvhat is your opinion &amp;c.</hi> but, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes said; <hi>This is the Doctrine of all the Fathers; this is the iudgment of the vvhole Church; it is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon sacred Scripture &amp;c. vvill you stand to it, or vvil you disclayme it?</hi> whereupon I common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued this answere; <hi>the doctrine is true in it selfe, though not seasonable for these times.</hi> But Maister <hi>D. King</hi> hauing not any such certainty of infallible grounds, could not but fluctuate in the instability of his priuate iudgment.</p>
               <p>To returne now vnto the conference of M. <hi>Vicechancellour</hi> with the aforesaid Doctour; he receiued a cold satisfaction vnto his hott de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. For the doctour, wondering that any difficulty should be made in this matter, ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered presently without any demurre; <hi>there are</hi> EVANGELICALL COVNSAILES; <hi>and no doubt can be made thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:177048:49"/>
               <p>And what was (thinke you) Doctour <hi>Kings</hi> reply vnto this graue, and confident assertion? Did he dispute against it? no; he could not. Did he gaynsay it? no; he durst not. Thus the renowned pulpit-Doctour, that could domineere ouer his poore inferiour, censure him, <hi>depraue</hi> him, vilify him with intollerable reproaches (such as he feared not to vtter, but I am ashamed to mention) stoode mute; not daring to disclose his opinion, which he could not iustify by any waight of reason.</p>
               <p>Now, if Doctour <hi>King</hi> will stand in deniall hereof, or any other be in doubt of my report, I protest, in the faith of a <hi>Catholique</hi> man, that I write this from the immediate relation of the Doctour himselfe, vnto whom I was ledd by the conduct of my good Angell; Farther, I am so well perswaded of his resolute iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and honest heart, that I dare boldy say; Doctour <hi>King</hi> shal neuer be able to procure his subscription against this doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> My appeale vnto the Archbishoppe of <hi>Canturbury;</hi> &amp; hovv episcopally it pleased his <hi>Grace</hi> to deale in the Matter.</head>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:177048:50"/>
               <p>AS I alwayes had comfort in my wronges, because I suffred <hi>for righteousnes sake;</hi> so I conceiued good hope, that the superiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate would rectify the proceedinges of his inferiour. Vvherfore, being oppressed with the iniuries of the <hi>Vicechancellour,</hi> I appealed vnto the <hi>Archbishoppe;</hi> thinking that his house had bene as <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> when <hi>iustice and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vvere lodged therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being admitted into his Graces presence, I vnfoulded the whole processe of this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; acquainting him first, with the doctrine, which I had preached. Secondly, with the groundes, and reasons wherevpon I built the same. Thirdly; with the intertainment, which it, and I for it, had found within the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The maine summe of his answere cōsisted in these two particulars. First; that he must defend the estimation of his <hi>vicechancellour,</hi> of whom a good opinion was generally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.<note place="margin">19. 21. vade, vende om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia cte.</note> Secondly; that the text of S. <hi>Math.</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly alleadged for that purpose) doth not afford the doctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes.</hi> And here his Grace (falling into <hi>Caluins</hi> false, and absurd exposition) sayd, that our Sauiour doth not here giue any <hi>Counsayle</hi> of Pouertie, but onely dismasked the hipocrisy of the yong man, being <hi>a proud, boasting Pharisee &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:177048:50"/>
               <p>My whole reply was, that as I sought not the impeachment of his <hi>vicechancellours</hi> credit, farther then he had wronged it him selfe by his indirect proceedinges, so, if I could not make my accusations good against him, I would be content to sustaine my former pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, with a greater augmentation.</p>
               <p>As for the text of <hi>S. Matth.</hi> I expounded it by <hi>S. Marke:</hi> who saith that Christ beholding the young man, loued him; which loue of Christ did cleare him from all suspition of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisy, and dissimulation. Besides; I humbly intreated his Grace to remitt him selfe, &amp; me, vnto the generall consent of <hi>Antiquity in this matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>Doctor Barlovv</hi> interposed his verdict: whom if I had knowne aswel by his face, as I knew him by his sermō, I had then appeached as a man of little honesty, or conscience: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he (in a sermon preached before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estie at Hampton Court, <hi>concerning the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Bisshopps</hi>) doth iustify the distinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Precepts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Counsayles;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">pag. fourth: before the end.</note> citing a text of <hi>S. Paul</hi> to that effect; &amp; yet now,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.25.</note> seing his Grace of <hi>Cāterburie</hi> disaffected towards this doctrine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e also spake agianst it. And thus it pleased D. <hi>Shavv</hi> (who proclaymed the Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> his <hi>Cales</hi> triumphe, and his <hi>London</hi> ruine) to crosse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im selfe with a flatt contradiction, rather
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177048:51"/> to dissent from his assertion, by whose fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour he had mounted into the chayre of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>Many occurrences there passed at that time; with the recapitulation whereof I will not now surchardge this little treatise. In conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; my Lord of <hi>Canturbury</hi> demaunded a copy of my sermon; which I deliuered vnto <hi>Maister Barcham</hi> (one of his Chaplaines) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the authorities, which do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ensue.<note place="margin">In the end of all.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The sermon was receiued, the authorities were returned vnto me againe: which made me thinke, that my cause should neuer come vnto an indifferent triall. And truly I sawe no probability of any triall. For though I gaue continual attendance at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> for the space of fifteene, or sixteene dayes, yet I was fedde with delayes, to my iust griefe and great expense.</p>
               <p>Vvherefore, seing no hope of redresse, where it lastly remayned, and was iustly expected, I retyred my selfe vnro some priuatenesse; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting my thoughtes in meditation bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God, and my owne soule.</p>
               <p>And now, in the sweetenesse of contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hauing God onely for the obiect of my comfort, I tooke an intellectuall reueiw of my cause, and all circumstances of the fore passed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177048:51"/> Businesse; commending the whole vnto God, the <hi>great</hi> &amp; soueraigne Iudge. For I had now resolued to be no farther troublesome vnto his Grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who had so little respect of truth, and no greater compassion of my wronges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Hovv being retired vnto priuate medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, J vvas found out by the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishoppe</hi> his Chaplayn, &amp; so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited by him to see his Lord. My resolution vpon a better course.</head>
               <p>VVHEN I had now remayned a fortnight space in my priuate meditations, his Graces Chaplaine (accompanied with a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of deuinity) made diligent enquiry after me; and finding me out,<note place="margin">D. Childer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; vvho is a Chaplayn also vnto his Grace.</note> he demaunded of me what was the reason of my long absence from his Lord; who (as he said) would write his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters effectually vnto his <hi>Vicechancellour</hi> for our reconciliation: so that I should be relieued, &amp; restored aswel vnto my former liberty of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, as vnto the fruition of my place.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:177048:52"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note>But here I remembred the answere of IEHV vnto the question of IORAM. <hi>Is it peace Iehu? vvhat peace</hi> (said he) <hi>vvhile the fornication of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel, thy mother, and her vvitchcraftes are yet in force?</hi> So, what reconciliation, <hi>vvhat peace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt me, and <hi>D. King,</hi> while truth was thus suppressed, and his heresy (worse then <hi>vvitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi>) stoode yet in force?</p>
               <p>Wherefore, after significatiō of my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minde to his Lord shippe, who now vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed in some sorte, to commiserate my vniust vexations: I answered, that I had greater res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the cause, for which I suffred, then of the punishmēt, which I did sustaine: assuring <hi>M. Barcham,</hi> that restitution vnto my place was not the principall part of my desire.</p>
               <p>For as God did require of me the constant iustification of his eternal truth, so I could not but require it also at their hands, who by their functiō (as Ministers) &amp; dignity (as Bishopps) were specially obliged thereunto.</p>
               <p>VVhereas he pressed me farther, with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of profit, and that I hindred the course of my preferment, by contending against the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Magistrates (<hi>vvho</hi> as he said, <hi>must stand one vvith an other</hi>) my reply was to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that I desired not to rise where truth must fall vertue is the pathe to Honour: Heauen must not be lost for earth: the plenty of riches
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177048:52"/> doth not recōpence the emptines of the soule: <hi>a good conscience is a continuall feast.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the magistrates I reuerenced their persons, and honoured their places; knowing that their <hi>povver is from God,</hi> but designed for the preseruation of his truth: which if I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned, let them strike me with the sworde of Iustice: but if they withstood it, yet, I must defend it with courage, as also I shall suffer for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with patience. For I alwayes had the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle of the wise man before mine eyes,<note place="margin">Ecclus. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Striue for the</hi> TRVTH <hi>vnto death &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVhich resolution in me though it sorted not with his liking, nor yet (perhapps) was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected frō a poore, oppressed scholler (whom his vncharitable aduersaries had determined either to bowe, or breake) yet he importuned me, at the least to see his Lord, and not to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his fauourable inclinatiō to do me good.</p>
               <p>VVhereupon I made a shew that I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hortly visite his Grace. And this I did, because I did probably collect, that my intention was by some meanes disclosed vnto him; whereby I might be defeated of that course, vpō which I was now wholly resolued.</p>
               <p>For me thought that God did speake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n my heart, as he spake sometimes vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> his seruant. <hi>Go foorth of thy land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.</note>
                  <hi>and from thy kindred, and from thy fathers house, and come into
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177048:53"/> the land, vvhich I shall shevv vnto thee.</hi> For, can any Church, or any faith be in that land, where the very grounds, and principles of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Christianity are dissolued, where there is no certaine foundation to builde Religion vpon? VVhere euery mans power is his reason to make good his Doctrine? VVhere an iniury sustayned for the truth, can find no redresse without treasonable conniuency to see the truth oppressed?</p>
               <p>But I will pretermitt (good Reader) here to make a speciall enumeration of my <hi>Motiues,</hi> drawing me vnto my finall resolutiō; for they will ensue orderly in the third, and last part of this Treatise. Onely consider (with me) now, with what conflict of flesh, and bloud I could intertayn this resolution, <hi>to come out of my Land, and from my kindred, and from my Fathers hovvse;</hi> with what grief I could forsake a noble Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersity, the company of my kindest friends, the comfort of my dearest familiars; other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moluments, which such a place doth actually yeald, and prepareth vnto greater.</p>
               <p>Howbeit (my Brethren) since there is bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shment indeed, where no place is left for truth, <hi>I esteeme all theis thinges as dongue, that I may gayne Christe;</hi> for he is my sufficient reward I did not conceiue that when I preached my do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine amōg you, I should haue giuen you such
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177048:53"/> an example thereof in mine owne person. But thancks be vnto him who disposeth all thinges sweetely for the benefite of his children.</p>
               <p>Finally (my brethren) I wish that you may enioy your <hi>contrey, which is aboue,</hi> without forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that, which is belowe. But if you cannot, by reason of the time; then looke vp vnto your eternity; let not your excellent spiritts abase themselues vnto the loue of trāsitory thinges; <hi>For behold I shevv you a more excellent vvay.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.11.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:177048:54"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART Contayning <hi>12. Motiues,</hi> vvhich persvvaded me to embrace the <hi>Catholicke</hi> Religion. Briefely, and naturally deriued out of the premises.</head>
            <p>S. AVGST. In psal. contra partem <hi>Donati</hi> Sitis <hi>Catholica</hi> quid sit, &amp; quid sit <hi>praecisum à vite:</hi> Si qui sint inter vos cauti, veniant, &amp; viuant de radice.</p>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:177048:54"/>
               <head>To the conscionable, and Ingenious Reader.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THOVGH</hi> the generall motiues vnto the <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion, are many, and vvaightie; yet the particular, vvhich issued out of this present businesse, vvere such, as cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced my vnderstanding, and svvayed my affection to approue, and embrace the same.</p>
               <p>ƲƲherefore <hi>(courteous Reader)</hi> aswel to procure thy good, as to iustify my selfe, and to satisfy others, J haue communicated them vnto thy vievv. For matter; they are the same novv, as vvhen J conceiued them in the beginning: for māner; they are brought forth in somevvhat a different shape.</p>
               <p>Thus much may suffice for thy instruction concerning these Motiues. Onely J may not forget to aduertise thee; that whereas through out their titles, J vse this perpetuall stile: <hi>The Protestantes &amp;c.</hi> (hovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177048:55"/> the most learned amongst them, differ in iudgement from the common sort: and in this respect, cannot be cōcluded in the generality of <hi>all</hi>) I haue not done this vvithout good consideration.</p>
               <p>For though the principall deuines in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> do vtterly distast the vayne opinions of <hi>D. King,</hi> and such like; yet, since by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique profession of the truth, they giue not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient notice vnto the vvorld of their <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> positions, J must inuolue them also in this cōmon accusation. And as they, against their knovvledge, do suffer a preiudice to fall vpon God his truth,<note place="margin">Corde cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ad iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiam; ore fit confessio ad salutem</note> they must likevvise, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their vvil, suffer an infamy to remaine vpon their ovvne persons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:177048:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The first Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> admit not a triall of their Religion by the testimony of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> vvhatsoeuer they pretend to the contrary.</head>
               <p>BECAVSE it is a preposterous deuise to iudge the former ages of the Churche by the later;<note place="margin">D. Field. pag. 204. VVe VVillingly admitt a triall by the Fathers; sayth he in the name of his Church.</note> therefore the courses of my study haue euer bene directed vnto a diligēt perusal of ancient <hi>Fathers;</hi> whose authority, simply cōsidered, as it may prepōderate our moderne writers; so, in reference vnto the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her witnesses (who is the iudge to define all controuersies) their testimonie is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all Authours whatsoeuer.</p>
               <p>Neither resolued I thus without serious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; &amp; especially, the graue counsayle of <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> did preuayle with me,<note place="margin">cōtra haeres. cap. 1. &amp; 2.</note> saying, that learned &amp; holy men did generally conspire in this opinion: <q>If any man wil dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Hereticall prauity from Catholike ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he must be furnished with a double helpe; <hi>first the Canon of sacred scripture: Secondlie the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177048:56"/> of the Catholique Churche:</hi>
                  </q> wherein three thinges inseparably concurre; <hi>Vniuersalitie, Antiquitie, Consent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reason of which prescriptiō is yealded by him to be this. The scripture is sublime; &amp;, forasmuch as all men sense it not alike, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to adioyne thereunto the continuall interpretation of the Church.</p>
               <p>Vpon this infallible ground (euident vnto all men of any apprehension) I builded my faith; conforming it alwayes vnto those Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox principles, which I had deriued out of the venerable <hi>Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence I assumed this doctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Counsailes,</hi> which as I deliuered out of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred volumes of Antiquity; so Antiquity it selfe deduced it (with me) out of the diuine Oracles of holy scripture. And therfore see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that my opiniō was clearly built vpon this fundation, I pressed it vncessantly, vntill my vniust Iudges were enforced to forsake this meanes of tryall, and, consequently to punish the <hi>Fathers</hi> in me, as I had spoken by them.</p>
               <p>But when I plainly sawe, that my doctrine could not be condemned without condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the auncient Church, &amp; that my Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were driuen to this extremity, I inferred, that <hi>their Religion could not be good;</hi> &amp; that <hi>their consciences vvere verie badde.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:177048:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The second Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> perferre their <hi>Reformed</hi> Congregations, before the ancient <hi>CATHOLIQVE</hi> Churche.</head>
               <p>AS my violent Iudges did palpably dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme the sentēce of the anciēt Church, so they vnreasonably required my submission vnto their reformed Congregations; which, as they be not comparable with the purity of the former, so their principall Doctours (<hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> &amp; <hi>Zvvinglius;</hi> men no lesse odious eache vnto the other, then both are hateful vnto the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) are no wayes matchable with the Patrones of my doctrine.<note place="margin">S August. S. Ambros. S. Hierom.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For as <hi>S. Gregory Nazianzen</hi> iustly excepted against the <hi>Arrians</hi> in this manner;<note place="margin">S, Gregory. Epistola 1. ad C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> contra Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianos.</note>
                  <hi>If our faith be but</hi> 30. <hi>yeares ould</hi> (400. <hi>yeares being passed since the incarnation of Christ) then our gospell hath bene preached in vayne; our martyrs haue dyed in vayne vntill this time,</hi> &amp;c. So if for a point of faith, I must remit my selfe vnto <hi>Luther, Zvvinglius, Caluin</hi> &amp; their reformed conuenticles, rather then vnto the holy <hi>Fathers,</hi> &amp; ancient <hi>Church;</hi> then surely the gospell hath bene miserably taught, and all our predecessors haue bene
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177048:57"/> pitifully deceiued for 1600. yeares since.</p>
               <p>Singular therefore was the folly, and partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of my Iudges, to detract authority from our blessed <hi>Fathers,</hi> &amp; to yealde it vnto <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> (men of as new a stampe in these tymes, as the <hi>Arriās</hi> were in <hi>S. Gregory Nazianzē</hi> his time) whose carnall appetites, and base condition of life, drew them to allow that in their doctrine which they performed in their practise; being contrary in both vnto the canon of scripture, and continuall succession of the Church.</p>
               <p>The consideration wherof did manifestly detect vnto me, that either their vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is very meane, or their will very peruerse; who feared not to disauthorise the <hi>Fathers,</hi> &amp; yet would not graunt me the same liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their brethren; in whom I neuer appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any thing otherwayes, then it was conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the prescription of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonant from hir Tradition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> brand the Catholique do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine vvith the name of <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE name of PAPISTS was first deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by a luxurious Apostata; inuentour also of the name of SACRAMENTARIES;<note place="margin">Luther.</note>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:177048:57"/> for so both <hi>Catholiques,</hi> and <hi>Zvvinglians</hi> stand indebted vnto him in theis respects.</p>
               <p>By the insolency of this man it came to passe, that as many other doctrines, so particularly this, had bene stamped with the imputation of <hi>Popery;</hi> whence it was that my <hi>Caluinian</hi> Iudges (calumniating both me and it) were pleased to fasten the note of <hi>Popery</hi> vpon it, and of a <hi>Papist</hi> vpon me.</p>
               <p>But since my grounds are meerely Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique (as you see) and since this doctrine it selfe is the common faith of ancient Churche; it followeth, either that it is no <hi>Popery,</hi> (as these men terme it) or that <hi>Popery</hi> (truly conceiued) is the very <hi>Catholique</hi> faith. But of the twoo, the later is more probable.</p>
               <p>VVherevpon I inferred this conclusion for my finall resolution; that POPERY was necessarily cōsequent vppon the true grounds of deuinity; &amp; therefore my Iudges betrayed their owne folly in this behalf; for asmuch,<note place="margin">VVhat Pope did euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise this and many other doctrines, vvhich are called Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery?</note> as by a condemnation of this doctrine, they must ineuitably confesse, that POPERY (well vnderstoode) is the doctrine of Antiquity; and that the <hi>Fathers</hi> were no lesse <hi>Papists</hi> herein then my selfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:177048:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> subuert the truest meanes of piety, and perfection.</head>
               <p>PERFECTION is not absolute in this life, but graduall; that is to say; men are perfit in a degree: some more, some lesse, according to their cooperation with diuine grace.</p>
               <p>To which end, and purpose, there are <hi>Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia perfectionis,</hi> Counsailes of perfection; as <hi>Vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie, Pouertie</hi> &amp;c. which remoouing the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments of perfection, are excellent meanes to cōduct vs therunto; in asmuch as they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw vs from the loue of the flesh and of the worlde, which are our capitall enemies assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs with their continuall delights, and pleasures.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Protestants</hi> (being in the number of them, of whom the Apostle, by prophetick spirit, spake long before; that <hi>they vvould not suffer vvholesome doctrine</hi>) renounce the aduise of their Sauiour; <hi>qui potest capere, capiat;</hi> they reiect the monition of <hi>S. Paul, consilium do;</hi> they cast behind them the common iudgment of ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> in this point. And whereas themselues are now caried away with the euill current of this worst age; they feare not, not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177048:58"/> only to disclayme the <hi>Fathers</hi> but irreligiously to slander them,<note place="margin">D. Benefield in his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</note> as <hi>men bevvitched herein vvith the errours of their time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it is that the plausibility of the first gospell seeketh not to cast any raynes vpon the feruour of nature, but yealdeth passage rather, and helpe vnto her precipitate course,</p>
               <p>S. PAVL was of a contrary opinion; witnesse his owne wordes, <hi>castigo corpus &amp;c.</hi> Antiquity was of an other disposition; witnesse <hi>S. Hierom</hi> in his epistle vnto Pope <hi>Damasus,</hi> and vnto the virgin <hi>Eustochium.</hi> VVitnesse S. <hi>Gregory Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> in his funerall oration vpon <hi>S. Basill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carnem logi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus fraenauit</note> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the whole quire of ancient Churche; which with a sweete heauēly harmony, aswell in practise, as in doctrine, hath commended vnto vs the restraint of lawfull thinges with a singular austerity of life.</p>
               <p>Theis things, being wholly opposite vnto the delicacy of <hi>Luthers</hi> spirit, are reputed <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> by him, and by his carnall sectaries; whose single faith (not clogged with the burthen of pious workes) can more easily mount vnto heauen. Thus are they lulled a sleepe in the cradle of security, dreaming of a victory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any striuing at all.</p>
               <p>Yf this be the way, vnto happinesse, the VVAY it selfe hath misled vs; our guides haue seduced vs; our teachers haue misinformed vs;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177048:59"/> the austerity of so many Saints registred in the canon of Gods woord, and recorded in the Calender of the Churche, hath bene practised in vayne; and the late gospell is more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table then the former.</p>
               <p>But whether I may rely more safely vpon the first, or last; I remit me vnto the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any man, that hath the sense of true piety lodged in his breast.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fift Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> corrupt the holy scripture in defence of their opinions.</head>
               <p>THE proper meanes designed by God to conuince Heresie, are two, to witt; <hi>sacred scripture;</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticall Tradition.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Heretiques are clearely refuted by the second, therfore they flye onely vnto the first, which they depraue, and mangle according to the liberty of their spirits. And this they performe partly in their translations, &amp; partly in their interpretation therof.</p>
               <p>Though many examples might be afforded in this kind, yet I need not seeke after further proofe, then this present businesse doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, wherof I now intreate. For wheras the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177048:59"/> words of our Sauiour are easy, and playne; <hi>all men</hi> DO NOT <hi>receiue this saying</hi> (to witt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning chastity) they render it thus: <hi>all men</hi> CANNOT <hi>receiue this saying;</hi> as though there were such an impossibilitie therein, that the freedome of will concurring with the grace of God, could not subdue the inclinations of corrupt nature.</p>
               <p>Hence Luther (the slaue of his affections) saith,<note place="margin">Tom. 7. in epist. ad vvolfgang.</note> that <hi>the propension of feruent nature in</hi> MAN <hi>towards a</hi> WOMAN <hi>is so created by God in his body, that it cannot be extinct by any vovves, &amp; therefore he, that resolueth to liue vvithout a</hi> WOMAN, <hi>must leaue the name of a</hi> MAN, <hi>and make himselfe to be plainly an Angell, or spirit. For it is by no meanes granted vnto him by God; so that it is aboue his strength to containe himselfe from a vvoman. And this is by the compulsiue vvord of God, vvilling, and commanding the same.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VVherefore the Counsayle of virginity is intollerable with them, that conceiue such an impossibilitie to fulfill it. <hi>To increase,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 5. serm. de matrimō.</note>
                  <hi>and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, it is not a precept</hi> (saith Luther) <hi>but it is more then a precept; it is implanted nature; it is as neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary as meate, and drinke. It is no more in the povver of Man to liue vvithout a vvoman, then to be a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and no man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In vayne then doth our Sauiour giue his aduise, and <hi>S. Paul</hi> his Counsayle. For, in Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:177048:60"/> gospell, it is more then a precept to auoid virginity. And yet my Iudges not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it to be a Counsayle, could deny it to be a precept. VVhich yet if it be so; why do they then make lesse conscience to fulfill a PRECEPT, then Catholiques do to follow a COVNSAYLE? for the neglect of the first is a sinne; but it is not so in the second; vnlesse wee tye our selues vnto it by a voluntary vow, being not constrayned therevnto by a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary commaund.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The sixt Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> are <hi>Iouinianists,</hi> and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore Heretiques, and not Catholiques, euen for this cause.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heres. 82.</note>S. <hi>Augustine</hi> (as a Register of the Cathol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Churche) doth witnesse that <hi>Iouinia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> broached this hereticall fancy,<note place="margin">See the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orat of S. August. his treatise. vide Ambros. 10. lib. Epist. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist 80. &amp; 81.</note> contrary to the receiued opinion of the whole Church. <hi>There is no more merit in the virginity of Nonnes, and other continent persons, then in chast mariadge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Counsailes of perfectiō denied by Iouinian.</note>The verie same opinion is defended, and embraced by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Caluinists;</hi> and they both conspire with <hi>Iouinian</hi> in this here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall tenent; that there is no greater perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in a virginall, then in a coniugall estate.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:177048:60"/>
               <p>And though it pleaseth Doctour <hi>Feild</hi> to say;<note place="margin">Pag. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> VVE <hi>do not approue any priuate opinion of</hi> IOVINIAN, <hi>contrary to the iudgment of Gods Churche;</hi> yet both he, and his Grace of <hi>Cant.</hi> (who approoued his booke) speake herein against their owne consciēce, yea myne owne experience in this particular businesse infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth me otherwayes then they pretend. And I desire no better witnesse to conuince them then <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> who writeth of this matter in the name of the vniuersall Churche.</p>
               <p>According to whose relation (compared with the generall opinion of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Caluinists</hi>) I do confidently affirme, that the <hi>Protestants</hi> are Heretiques in this behalfe; and that, for this cause (besides many others; which I spare to deale in at this present) they are exiled out of the society of the auncient Catholick Churche.</p>
               <p>For <hi>S. Augustine</hi> protesteth (in the perora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his aforesaid treatise) that <hi>vvhosoeuer doth maintayne any of these Heresies, vvhich he hath recorded before, he is not a</hi> CATHOLIQVE <hi>Christian;</hi> and therefore an <hi>Hereticall</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. VVhich censure doth necessarily fall vpon my <hi>Caluinian</hi> iudges, and vpon all such, as concurre with their irreligious opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:177048:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The seuenth Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> accommodate their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion vnto the state, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time.</head>
               <p>AS the formes of <hi>Ecclesiasticall gouerments</hi> are varied by the <hi>Caluinists</hi> in sondry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according vnto the state, vnder which they liue, so their Doctrines are framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the times, and made sutable vnto the policy of their common wealths. Pipe state; &amp; dance Churche. Religion must haue no coate otherwise, then measure is taken by the State.</p>
               <p>A iust experience whereof I had in the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of this businesse. For as the more grosse, and senselesse <hi>Caluinists</hi> in <hi>England</hi> do Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically confound <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles</hi> with <hi>Legall Precepts,</hi> so others, more regardfull of the time, wherein they liue, then of the truthe which they should professe, do willingly yeald (for if they should do otherwayes, they should speake against their iudgment, and conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce) that this distinction is founded in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, and propounded by the Churche; but
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177048:61"/> they say, that it is not a Doctrine seasonably to be deliuered in theis times.</p>
               <p>And might not this statizing reason aswell pleade for <hi>Arrius</hi> his damnable Heresie, being more generaly disaffected by the state in those times, <hi>dum totus mundus ingem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it sub Arrianis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo;</hi> as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> speaketh.<note place="margin">Contra Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But I considered first; that truth is not to be impugned, and suppressed, as the common fury of <hi>Caluinists</hi> hath euer sought to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishe it, to the vttermost of their power. In which respect I found my selfe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily affected, for the reiection of their heresy in this behalfe. And I trust it was not without speciall motion of that spirit, which breacheth in the whole body of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church, and consequently in euery constant member of the same.</p>
               <p>Secondly, though time beare the blame, yet men are in the fault; and therefore seeing that the open enimies of truthe did barke, when hir secret frends did hold their pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; I conceiued that it was my duty rather to change the time from euill into good, then to suffer it to growe from euill into worse.</p>
               <p>And though some men (assisted with power to punish that, which their peeuish fancie disaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected) did beare me downe by violence, yet I tooke no lesse comfort by this iniurie which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177048:62"/> they offred vnto me, thē courage by the course which they helde against my doctrine. For I saw that they rather obserued prophane policy to force me vnto silence, then either shew of iustice or piety in proceeding against my (fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly supposed) crime, or waight of reason in cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing my vnderstanding. And why? they are the slaues of time, but not disciples of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The eight Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> can patiently suffer the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the <hi>Creede</hi> &amp;c. to be viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but they are seuere in those thinges, that repugne their vtility, or sensuality vvhatsoeuer.</head>
               <p>EVERIE truth, in respect of God reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, and the Church propounding it, is of equal necessity to be beleeued; howbeit, in respect of the matter it selfe; one truth may be of greater consequence; and dignity then an other. And yet it is not the greatnesse of the matter it selfe, but the manner of reuealing, which tyeth vs to a necessity of beleefe.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:177048:62"/>
               <p>I will instance in this present businesse. The distinction of <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles</hi> from <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Precepts,</hi> is a truth to be accepted vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of saluation. VVhy? because it is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently reuealed vno vs by God, and fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the Catholique Church; so that it is either wilfull ignorance, not to knowe it, or extreme obstinacy to withstand it. But yet the Articles of the Creede, which are the first elements of faith, commended vnto vs by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall tradition, may iustly be reputed more waightie, in respect of the matter, which is handled therin; as namely <hi>the descent of Christ into hell.</hi> VVhich article of faith, is admirably peruerted by the Ministers in <hi>England,</hi> in so much as 3. or 4. sondry opinions thereof are freely, &amp; vncontroulably deliuered by them, vnto their simple flockes.</p>
               <p>I might instance in their different opinions about the Sacraments, and other high miste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of saluation, wherein fanaticall spirits ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiate without any reproofe. But I willingly pretermit these, and come to other particular points of doctrine, which I preached amongst them without impeachment.</p>
               <p>First, against <hi>Caluin</hi> his hereticall Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme destroying the vnity of the diuine es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, I taught, with the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creede, and all antiquity; that Christ is <hi>Deus de Deo,</hi> hauing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177048:63"/> the same substance that is in the Father, really communicated vnto him in his eternall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>Secondly; with <hi>S. Gregory, Damascen,</hi> the <hi>Greeke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Latine</hi> Churche I taught, that Christ assumed our nature perfit, and complete in the very instant of his conception: contrary to the absurd opinion of diuers <hi>Caluinisticall Protestants,</hi> who auouch that his incarnation was by temporall degrees, and not by entire perfection in an instant.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; that God was only the permissiue, not any impulsiue cause of sinne; though <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> blaspheme to the contrary, and deride the distinction.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Christ crying out, <hi>Deus meus, Deus meus &amp;c.</hi> was not in a traunce; he suffred no tormēts of hel; dyed not by degrees (as though his senses decayed by little &amp; little) but in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit sense, payne, obedience, patience, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, constancy, he rendred vppe his righteous soule <hi>a voluntarie</hi> sactifice for sinne. But the cōmon opinion of <hi>Caluinistes</hi> is contrary vnto this position.<note place="margin">Filius &amp; spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus sanctus quoniā non sunta se diē &amp; horam iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicij nesciūt a se, pater autem quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiama se est cit a se. Hil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r in Math.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly; Christ was not ignorant of the day of iudgement either as God or man: not as God; for though he knew it not primarily, &amp; originally as of him selfe (being not God of him selfe) yet did he knowe it secondarily by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177048:63"/> way of communication from the Father.<note place="margin">Respectu or dinis non temporis.</note> Not as Man, for though he did not know it Ex <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ humanitatis,</hi> yet did he know it IN <hi>naturâ humanitatis,</hi> as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> distinguisheth.<note place="margin">lib. epist. 8. cap. 42. In M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rc. 13.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And this doctrine is contrary to <hi>Caluin</hi> his blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous glosse; to wit, <hi>Chistus communem habuit cum Angelis ignorantiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These, and many such like doctrines (dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly opposite to <hi>Caluin</hi> his tenents) as he is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth (for though his disciples call him <hi>a great light of the gospell,</hi> yet I rather approue the censure of D. <hi>Hunnius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiz.</note> a famous Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, saying, that <hi>Caluin is an Angell of darkenesse</hi>) could passe vnnoted, &amp; vncontrouled by my Caluinian Iudges, and all other adherents vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that faction.</p>
               <p>VVhy then is this distinction of <hi>Preceptes</hi> &amp; <hi>Counsailes</hi> so hatefull vnto the <hi>Caluinists?</hi> Alas, it toucheth their copy hould; most of them being either maried men, or bēding that way: and therfore let <hi>Sacraments, Christ Church &amp;c.</hi> be abused, nay let many points of Catholique doctrine be preached by Orthodox deuines, yet they are more attētiue vnto the suppression of this truthe, and the like, which doth more directly concerne their carnall pleasure, and wordly profit.</p>
               <p>For they that haue sould themselues to be the exact vassalls of their owne affections, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177048:64"/> other mens wills, are carefull to prouide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any thing right, or wrong; true, or false; which may be preiudiciall therevnto; rather attending what it is which wil maintayne their sensuality, then what is orthodox in sound deuinity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ninth Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> do vnconscionably im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the knovvne, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest truth.</head>
               <p>SINCE the controuersies of Religion are many in number, and intricate in nature, it was my desire (from the beginning of my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the study of sacred Theology) to find out the true Church, that so I might referre my selfe vnto her decision, and rest within her bosome.</p>
               <p>For which cause I wholly employed my selfe in turning ouer the volumes of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Fathers;</hi> and whatsoeuer I found clearely expressed by their vniforme testimony; I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted that (according to <hi>Vincentius</hi> his rule) as the iudgment of the Churche.</p>
               <p>Amongst other Doctrines (which seeme <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> vnto the new Euangelists) I receiued this
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177048:64"/> particular from their instruction; so clearly taught, so conformably witnessed, so ioyntly approoued, that, if the grounds of Religion be not vncertain, then this Doctrine is abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely free from all exception. And for proofe hereof, I remit me vnto the sentences of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> wherwith I thought it meete to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this discourse.</p>
               <p>VVherefore, since they that glory in the Fathers (and want neither witt, nor learning for this matter) do impugne this doctrine, and punish her professours; how can I thinke, that they do not fight against their conscience, &amp; reason? And how can I thinke that any truth will find intertaynement at their hands, when this truth so potent, and so irrefragable: is thus fondly reiected by my <hi>Caluinian</hi> iudges?</p>
               <p>But whom haue they condemned? me? a brother some times of their gospell, a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duate of their schooles, a Minister of their Church? No; but in me, and with me, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Antiquity, the gray headed <hi>Fathers,</hi> the venerable Doctours, yea holy scripture it selfe is censured by my vnworthy iudges.</p>
               <p>VVherefore, as <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Apolog: Iusti Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij pag. 11.12.</note> the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> wrote vnto the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> so may I testify, and proclayme vnto these men. <hi>The ancient deuines, vvho vvere the light of the Church, you intreate at your ovvne pleasure; honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:177048:65"/> &amp; extolling them in vvords but reiecting them in deede; endeuoring to shake them out of our hands, vvhose holy and diuine testimonies vvee should vse against you. VVee see that you vvil neuer submitte your selues vnto the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, as the Patriarch concludeth, that he will haue no intercourse with the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> forasmuch as he is taught by S. Paul to <hi>auoyd an heretick, after the first, or second admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> so I (being persecuted by men of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) am bound to auoyde them; knowing (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> speaketh) that such (as they) <hi>are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by their ovvne iudgements.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The tenth Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants,</hi> for vvant of better meanes to conuince the <hi>Catholiques,</hi> propose vnto them questions of capitall daunger.</head>
               <p>I HAVE often heard the Catholiques com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that, where as <hi>they are persecuted for righteousnesse sake,</hi> and for their Religion; yet they are traduced with the crime of obstinacy, disobedience, treason, and such like odious imputations.</p>
               <p>But aboue the rest, their iust greife (arising
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:177048:65"/> from vniust vexations, did seeme to deserue great compassion, forasmuch as their life, and liuelyhood is allwayes in the mercy of a most vnmercifull law, touching <hi>Reconciliation</hi> and the SVPREMACY; matters of high, and capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall nature.</p>
               <p>Touching the later of these two, I can say more,<note place="margin">Doctour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray.</note> because the bloudy heart of a Caluinist did seeke my ruine &amp; subuersion thereby. For wheras, in my sermons, I continually gaue this stile vnto his excellent Maiestie; viz. <hi>in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and aboue all persons, for iustice, and iudgment, supreme Head, and Gouernour;</hi> the <hi>Caluinist</hi> suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting me not to stand throughly affected to the kings <hi>Supremacy,</hi> according to the purport of the law (whereby his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath asmuch spirituall Iurisdictiō, as euer the Pope, <hi>de facto,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">26. Hent 8. chap. 1. 1 Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard 6 I Elizab. See theis things excellently discoursed a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine against the fift part of Sir. Ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ookes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</note> had in <hi>England;</hi> and, by vertue of his said su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, power of <hi>Excommunication</hi> is graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the lord Chancellour vnto the Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates vpon Appeales, from the Archbishopp of Canterbury his courts.) wished M. Vice chancellour to examine me vpon this point, &amp; to require my opinion therein.</p>
               <p>VVhich seueritie though it was then decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet if that other <hi>Caluinist</hi> had bene in offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (as lately he was) all men may easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue into what extremity of perill I had bene cast.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:177048:66"/>
               <p>For though I euer did, and shall attribut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that right vnto his Majestie, which, by the law temporall (not dissenting from law diuine) is annexed vnto his imperiall crowne; yet I must cōfesse that I did purposely moderate his title of Supremacy (as the law hath established it) because I allwayes conceiued, that the stile of <hi>Defensor fidei</hi> (giuen vnto the crowne of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> by the Pope) did more properly belong vnto him, then the other, which was transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Pope vnto the Crowne, by the violence of a King,<note place="margin">Hent. 1.</note> and by the flattery of his subiects.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos cap. 6. In epist. 54. ad Mycon.</note>And if Doctour <hi>Airay</hi> had made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of his Maisters iudgment, he would rather haue condescended vnto the equity of my opinion, then sought to draw my life into the certainty of such a danger.</p>
               <p>But theis men are so possessed with malice, &amp; adulation, that they rather desire to satisfie their owne passions, &amp; to winne fauour from their Superiours, then to speake, or do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truth which pleadeth for it selfe within their corrupt hearts, and dayly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth them before the throne of greatest iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:177048:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The eleuenth Motiue.</hi> The <hi>Protestants</hi> Manner of proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Catholiques,</hi> and <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion, is absurd in reason, and vnequall in Justice. And hence they are prooued to be <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN my perusall of the ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> and Ecclesiasticall histories, I did very often ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue theis two things. First; that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church had wisedome to discerne Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall innouations. Secondly; that she had power to enact necessary lawes for the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression therof; so that an Heresy could not escape hir censure, nor an Heretick hir iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Popery</hi> therefore be Heresy, and <hi>Papists</hi> Hereticks (as some fanatically brand them) then surely the Catholick <hi>Protestāticall</hi> Church is able to shew, that shee, in all ages, hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned this Heresy, and that she hath her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per lawes to proceede against Hereticall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours: If not so; then doubtlesse shee is no more Catholick, then the furious Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Donatists, Arrians,</hi> and such like; who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:177048:67"/> afflicted the true Church against all order of iustice; being neuer able to shew any Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick predecessours, who maintayned their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, nor any lawes made by them to correct the impugners thereof.</p>
               <p>That this is the condition of <hi>Protestants,</hi> I am a witnesse by their disorderly proceeding against the Doctrine, which I deliuered out of the conforme testimonies of the Church.</p>
               <p>For wheras it pleased my <hi>Caluinian</hi> iudges to call it POPISH, <hi>erroneous, false, lying,</hi> absurd Doctrine; they could not reprooue it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, then <hi>Arrians,</hi> and <hi>Donatists,</hi> that is to say, by reiecting the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and by a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous processe, without any legall course.</p>
               <p>And though I required them to deale with me as with an <hi>Heretick,</hi> by refelling my doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and by proceeding <hi>Canonically</hi> against me; yet they oppressed me with authoritie alone; hauing their will for reason, and their power for iustice.</p>
               <p>But for asmuch as I haue such abundant proofe for the verity of my doctrine, and that their opinion is condemned in the Churche for no lesse then Heresy, (by <hi>Syricius,</hi> Bishopp of Rome;<note place="margin">Ambros: 10. lib epist: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. 80. &amp; 81.</note> and a Counsayle there: by <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> Bishopp of <hi>Millayn,</hi> and a Counsayle there) I appeach them confidently as Hereticks for embracing <hi>Iouinianisme;</hi> as Hereticks for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:177048:67"/> of Antiquity; and therefore as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks culpable of singular pride.</p>
               <p>VVhich infamy if they can washe away from themselues by learning, &amp; honesty, then I will retract my sentence, &amp; confesse my selfe to be an Heretick (for the one of vs must needs be Hereticks) howsoeuer euery ingenuous, &amp; indifferent man must needs confesse, that they did not cary themselues as they should haue done to prooue me guilty of this crime.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>The tvveluth Motiue.</hi> The superiour Magistrates amonst the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> concurre vvith their subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to suppresse the truth, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse the patrones therof, against all equity, and conscience.</head>
               <p>THOVGH there be a very nere connexion betwixt the superiour, and inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, yet since all Magistracy is ordayned for the conseruation of truth, and iustice as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in the Church, as in the commonwealth (nay much more in the first, then in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond) it is very requisite, that the superiour should yeald redresse, where the inferiour hath done a wrong; and that rather respecting
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177048:68"/> the cause, then the persons, he should minister equity vnto both with an impartiall hand.</p>
               <p>For which consideration, when my petty iudges had oppressed me according to their owne humours, and passions; I appealed vnto my Lord of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Grace; in regard of his Academicall soueraignty ouer me, and them (being our honourable <hi>Chancellour</hi>) and much more in respect of his Archiepiscopall dignity; he being the Primate of our Church; persuading my selfe also, that as he is more high in place, so he would haue bene more equall in iustice; and specially in this cause, since his Grace hath sufficiently manifested himselfe (and hath bene so generally reputed) to be auerse from <hi>Caluinisme;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tempora mutant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, &amp; nos muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ini llis.</note> &amp; my hope was, that his present place had not changed his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vnderstanding.</p>
               <p>To whom though I truly vnfolded the whole businesse, and acquainted him with all circumstances therunto belonging, yet his Grace seeming to fauour Caluins opiniō (but how cōscionably, it shalbe now referred vnto the iudge of all the world; and he will reueale it in the appointed time) putt me of with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall delayes.</p>
               <p>But his Grace had iust reason to expect a strong resolution in me; since I did appeale vnto him to do me iustice only, &amp; much more
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177048:68"/> to giue his verdict vpon the Doctrine it selfe. For, otherwayes, no fauour, nor benefit what soeuer could yeald contētment vnto my grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued soule.</p>
               <p>I leaue it vnto others to consider, how his Grace standeth affected vnto truth: as for me, I trust, that I haue giuen a sufficient demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, on my part, that I would rather loose my liberty of speach, then that shee should want my vttermost defence.</p>
               <p>Here the indifferent Reader may also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue with me, that if my Doctrine had bene liable vnto a iust censure, then surely his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce would haue made no stay to condemne it in solemne manner; especially since it was so publiquely taught, so earnestly defended by me; and since I did now entirely desire him to do me iustice without any fauour.</p>
               <p>But since this Doctrine was not subiect vnto his condemnation, why then had his Grace so little reuerence vnto the eternall truth of God, and so small respect of me, that he would suffer it to be so indignely censured by his vicegerent, &amp; leaue me helplesse from such iniurious oppression? his pretenses to the contrary (if he haue any) are nothing but smoaky euaporations.</p>
               <p>I am nothing, and worse then nothing. But I pleaded for iustice. In what? In a point
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177048:69"/> of faith. VVhen? being violently oppressed. Before whom? my most proper iudge, to whom the decision of theis things doth most fitly appertayne. For what end? the honour of God, and his gospells sake; which I truly deliuered, and for which I was shame fully intreated.</p>
               <p>The testimonies of the Fathers touching <hi>Euangelicall Counsayles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:177048:69"/>
            <head>TO M. DOCTOR KING DEANE OF CHRIST-CHVRCH in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Vicechancellour of the Vniuersity, H. L. vvisheth health and saluation in Christ IESVS.</head>
            <p>SIR, <hi>though your vvill vvas your lavv to punish me vvithout my offence, yet it shall not be your sanctuary to defend your selfe, vvithout more sufficient reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For as you conuented me before a selected</hi> Caluinian <hi>assembly, so novv I conuent you, and them, before all men in the assured confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my good cause, and in the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble peace of my sincere heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And since you dealt vvith me as a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, by the strength of your authoritie, you must geue me leaue novv to deale vvith you as a Scholler, by the validity of argumēts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally; because I vvish your future happinesse, J cannot omitt to acquaynt you vvith your present misery, vvhich I vvill lay forth before your eyes in Syllogistical manner
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:177048:70"/> and then I vvill referre you vnto the cōsul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of your ovvne heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Whatsoeuer doctrine is founded v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Scripture, according to the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable opinion of the ancient Church, that is a point of Catholique faith.</p>
            <p>But the doctrine of <hi>Euangelicall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayles</hi> is founded vpon Scripture, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conformable opinion of the ancient Church.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Doctrine of <hi>Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Counsayles</hi> is a point of Catholique faith.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is a maxime in all Christian schooles.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is prooued by the ensuing testimonies of the Fathers: vyhose vniforme ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict in this behalfe is the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whosoeuer doth obstinately im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne any point of Catholique faith, he is an heretike.</p>
            <p>But Doctour <hi>Kinge, D. Aglionby,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:177048:70"/> D. Airay, D. Hutton, D. Benefield &amp;c.</hi> do obstinately impugne a point of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faith.</p>
            <p>Therfore <hi>D. King, D. Aglionby &amp;c.</hi> are heretikes.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is granted by all men of iudgment, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by S. <hi>Augustines</hi> rule.<note place="margin">De haeres ad Quod vult D. in pero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is prooued by their owne proceedings against me in this particular.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Euery heretike is bound to recant his heresy, or els he is liable to the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, decreed in the Canonicall lavv of the Church.</p>
            <p>But <hi>D. King, D. Aglionby, &amp;c.</hi> are heretikes.</p>
            <p>Therfore <hi>D. King, D. Aglionby &amp;c.</hi> are bound to recant their heresie, or els they are liable to the punishmēt decreed in the Canonicall lavv of the Church.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is cleare of it selfe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is prooued already.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And because it shal appeare yet more
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:177048:71"/> sensibly, I pray you to consider, that vvhosoeuer reiecteth the ioynt consent of FATHERS in a poynt of doctrine (as <hi>D. King</hi> doth herein) he is an heretick: and this I vvil briefly declare by foure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidences.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epist 1. ad Leon. cap. 1.</note>FIRST: by the testimony of <hi>Flauia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> saying: <hi>Haeretici est praecepta Patrum declinare, &amp; instituta eorum despicere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In Concil. Chalced.</note>SECONDLY: by the testimony of <hi>Eudoxius</hi> admitted in a general Councel: <hi>qui non consentit sacrosanctorum Patrum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positionibus, alienat se ab omni sacerdotali communione, &amp; a Christi praesentia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">See Sozom. l. 7. c. 12.</note>THIRDLY: by the procedings of the most Christian emperour <hi>Theodosius</hi> against the proud, distracted Hereticks: who would not submitt themselues vnto the iudgements of the venerable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">See Vincent. Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. 42.</note>FOVRTHLY: by the practise of the <hi>Ephesine</hi> Counsayle agaynst <hi>Nestorius:</hi> vvho vvas iudged an heretick, not onely
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:177048:71"/> in regard of the matter it self, vvherein he erred damnably, but in regard of the manner of triall by the holy <hi>Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">veterum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretum scripta perdiscere de digna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us est. See So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. l. 7. c. 32.</note> vvhich his contemptuous spirit did vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly decline. Many also of those Fathers by vvhose testimony the cause was then handled agaynst <hi>Nestorius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">NOTA</note> are the very same, vvhose verdicts I shall novv pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce agaynst <hi>D. King,</hi> and against his abettours vvhosoeuer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:177048:72"/>
            <head>An honourable <hi>grand-Jury</hi> of 24. Fathers, testifying the distinction betwixt <hi>Legall Precepts,</hi> &amp; EVAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GELICALL COVNSAYLES, by their vniforme verdict.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1. FATHERS OF THE LATIN CHVRCH.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">CYPRIANVS (anno Dom. 240.) de dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipl. &amp; hab. virg. sect. 17. &amp; 18. Serm. de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuit. Christi.</note>OVR Lord doth exhort vs vnto Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but he imposeth not the yoke of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity. Though mariadge be good, and insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by God, yet Virginity is more excellent, which the commandement doth not compell vs vnto, but the COVNSAYLE OF PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FECTION doth perswade.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">OPTAT. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuitan (370) lib 6. contra Parmenian.</note>Virginity is a thing of will, not of necessity. VVherefore <hi>S. Paul</hi> answered that <hi>touching vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins he had no</hi> PRECEPT <hi>of our Lord; but yet he gaue</hi> COVNSAYLE &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">AMEROSIVS (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>80) lib. 10. ep. 82.</note>The Apostle doth not cōmand Virginity, but perswade it; for that is not commanded, which is <hi>aboue the lavv.</hi> No woman is cōpelled
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:177048:72"/> vnto a single life by the authority of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, but there are rewards proposed vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers virtues. VVe do not reprehend the one to praise the other, but we praise all, that those things may be preferred, which <hi>are chiefest.</hi> Mariadge is honourable, but <hi>Virginity is more honourable;</hi> for <hi>he that giueth his virgin in Mariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, doth vvell; but he that giueth hir not, doth better.</hi> VVherefore, that which is good, is not to be auoyded; but that, which is better, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. And for this cause Virginity is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, but proposed; whence the Apostle sayeth; <hi>Concerning virgins I haue no</hi> PRECEPT, <hi>but I giue</hi> COVNSAYLE. <hi>Counsayles</hi> are more then <hi>Precepts;</hi> and therefore when one sayd vnto our Sauiour, <hi>all theis things haue I done,</hi> (viz. pertayning vnto the law) our Lord answered, &amp; sayd; <hi>sell all that thou hast,</hi> &amp;c. VVhich was a <hi>Counsayle</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That which is commanded,<note place="margin">HIERO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MVS (382) contra Ioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. lib. 1. de verbis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post. 1 Cor. 7.25.</note> must be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and, if we do it not, there is a punishment remayning. For that is commanded in vayn, which is left in the free choyce of him, vnto whom it is commanded. Meruayle not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if, in this prouocatiō of the flesh, the life of Angells be not required of vs, but taught vnto vs. For where <hi>Counsayle</hi> is giuē, there is the free will of him that offereth; but where a <hi>Precept</hi> is, there is a necessity in him that obayeth, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:177048:73"/>
               <p>Our Lord did not giue a <hi>Counsayle,</hi> but a <hi>Precept</hi> vnto vs in his ghospell,<note place="margin">AVGVSTINVS; (400) Serm. 61. de Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</note> that we should loue our enimyes. A <hi>Precept</hi> is one thing, but a <hi>Counsayle</hi> is an other. There is <hi>Counsayle</hi> giuen to preserue Virginity, to abstayn from wyne, and flesh; to sell our goodes, and to giue them vnto the poore. But to do good, and to decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from euill, and to keepe iustice, it is a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> Of Virginity it is sayd; <hi>he that can receiue it, let him receiue it;</hi> but it is not sayd of iustice; he that <hi>can</hi> do it, let him do it: for <hi>euery tree, that bringeth not forth good fruict, shall be hevven dovvne, and cast into the fire:</hi> He that perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a <hi>Counsayle,</hi> shall haue the greater glory; but he that keepeth not a <hi>Precept,</hi> shall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vnlesse he repent. <hi>Vide plura in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erinis coning. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>de sanctâ Virginitate, cap.</hi> 14. &amp;c. Consider also how D. <hi>Field</hi> doth confesse,<note place="margin">Of the Church. pag. 170.</note> that AVGVSTINE <hi>is the greatest of all the Fathers, and vvorthiest deuine, that the Church of God euer had since the Apostles times;</hi> whose iudgement in this point is conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the other Fathers, and founded eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently vpon the holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">PAVLINVS (4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.) ep. 4. ad Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ru Sul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it</note>Our Lord was the good <hi>Samaritane,</hi> and <hi>S. Paul</hi> was the Maister of the Inne, who did supererogate, when he added this <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle</hi> (beyond the <hi>Precept</hi>) concerning the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall estate.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:177048:73"/>
               <p>Virginity is not vnder the cōmandement;<note place="margin">SEDVLIV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (450.) in 1. Cor. 7.</note> for then Mariadge were forbydden. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>S. Paul</hi> had no precept touching <hi>Virgins;</hi> that being of greater reward, which is offered, and not commanded.</p>
               <p>The Apostle had no <hi>Precept,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">EVIGENTIVS (480) in praefat ad Mommum.</note> but he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his <hi>Counsayle</hi> touching Virgins; and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby he did erogate more then he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
               <p>Some are not iudged, and raigne; who transcend the precepts of the law by a more perfitt vertue, and performe more,<note place="margin">GREGOR. Magnus (600.) lib. 26 in Iob. cap. 24. &amp; 25.</note> by a prompt deuotion, then they were obliged vnto. For whereas our Lord sayeth; <hi>Go, and sell all that thou hast,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">All men are bound vnto perfection as farre as the cōdition of their life can permitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but no man is bound to the cōdition of virginall life. &amp;c.</note> &amp;c. it is not spoken ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally vnto all, but, by a speciall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, vnto the perfitt. For if it did bynde all men, then it were a sinne to possesse any thinge. But it is one thing, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed vnto all, and an other thing, which is commanded vnto those, that aspire vnto perfection. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> preached the gospell freely &amp;c. <hi>Vide plura, lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>The Apostle did supererogate,<note place="margin">BEDA (750.) in Luc. 10.</note> when he gaue the <hi>Counsayle</hi> of Virginity, whereof there is no precept. Likewise; whereas our Lord, did ordayn, that those, who preach the gospell, should liue thereby, <hi>S. Paul</hi> would not vse that power, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:177048:74"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>LMVS (1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.) in 1. Cor 7 25.</note>There is no <hi>Precept</hi> touching Virgins, but Counsayle onely. Our Lord did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Virginity, least he might seeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Mariadge. VVherefore he loueth Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins more then others, inasmuch as they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that, where vnto they were not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">BERNARD. (140.) de praecept. &amp; dispens. cap. 10.</note>The rule of <hi>S. Bennet</hi> is proposed vnto euery man, it is imposed vpon none. It doth profitt, if it be deuoutely vndertaken, &amp; kept; and yet it doth not hurt, if it be not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. It is a voluntary thing, and not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary; howbeit, he that doth voluntarily intertayn it, must necessarily retayn it; for he maketh it a necessity vnto himself, inasmuch as euery man is bound to performe his vowes. But that is an happy necessity, which prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs vnto better thinges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:177048:74"/>
               <head>§. 2. FATHERS OF THE GREEKE CHVRCH.</head>
               <p>THOSE thinges,<note place="margin">ORIGINES (anno Dom. 230) in Rom. cap. 15.</note> which we performe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our obligation, we performe not by reason of any <hi>precept;</hi> as for example. <hi>Virginitie</hi> is not a debt, which we ought to pay; neither are we commanded thereunto: but we offer it [vnto God] aboue that, which we are bound vnto. For S. <hi>Paull</hi> sayeth; <hi>Concerning Virgins I haue no commandement of our Lord, but I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saylle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are instituted two māners of liuing in the Church of God.<note place="margin">EVSEBIV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (330.) de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrat. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangel. lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> The one doth euen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede our nature, and the cōmon disposition of men: for it desireth not mariadges, nor chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor welth; but declineth from the vsual life of other men, and our of the singular loue of celestiall thinges, is addicted only vnto the seruice of God. This is a perfit manner of life in Christian Religion.</p>
               <p>VVho euer was the author of keeping Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity? Nay,<note place="margin">ATHANASIVS (340.) de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnat verbi. He meaneth not that any precept doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that Christ deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his rules. &amp;c.</note> who taught not that this vertue could not be performed? And yet our Sauiour hath bene so powerfull in theis precepts, that children, not ripe for the discipline of lawes, do professe virginity, which is aboue the law,</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:177048:75"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>LIVS <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate.</note>VVe intend not to impose virginity vpon men, by way of <hi>Precept,</hi> but we insinuate the cleanenes therof vnto such, as purpose to buy the pretious iewell therof. For, <hi>concerning vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, I haue not the precept of our Lord, onely I geue counsaille.</hi> God did not appoynt vnto vs a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of virginity, either in the law, or in the gospel. For he that had instituted Matrimony, and bad men to <hi>multiply &amp;c.</hi> by what precept could he inioyne virginity? He would not that the merit of so excellent a vertue should be vnder the compasse of a law; but he would haue it to be the tokē of a noble minde, which freely, and without the necessity of a precept, doth, for the desire of vertue, performe that, which surpasseth all the commandements, &amp; is beyond the measure of our humane nature. Mariadge is naturall, but virginity is aboue nature, and is not tyed by the bondes of the law: it offereth vnto God the rare vertue of incorruption, as a pretious gift. Therefore out Lord did no where geue vs a law of virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; knowing well, that it is proper vnto a soule, which is addicted vnto the study of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For when he hard one saying; <hi>it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to marry;</hi> he (purposing to shew the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of virginall estate) answered; <hi>all receiue not this saying.</hi> And the Apostle (following him) <hi>commaundeth</hi> those thinges in his epistles,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:177048:75"/> which are necessary in this life; but he decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing of virgins. Onely, when he was asked touching this matter, he sayd (in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Lord) <hi>Concerning virgins I haue no precept, but I giue counsayle &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In our Christian lawes,<note place="margin">NAZIANZ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (380. Orat. 1. in Iulian.</note> some things do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a necessity of obaying, and they can not be pretermitted without danger.<note place="margin">The vvord (lavv) is not taken pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely here for a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, but generally for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vvil of God.</note> Other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bynde vs not with any necessity, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in our free will, and choyce. VVherefore if any man keepe them, he shall haue much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and reward; and they that fulfill them not, may not feare any perill thereby.</p>
               <p>God doth not command impossible thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;<note place="margin">CHRYSOST. (380.) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 8. de Poenit.</note> for many do exceede the cōmandements themselues. He doth no where command vs to preserue virginity, and to possesse nothing. VVherefore <hi>S. Paul</hi> sayeth; <hi>Concerning Virgins I haue not any precept from our Lord; onely I giue Counsayle.</hi> Thou seest no law here, but an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise; thou seest him not commanding, but perswading; the first is a matter of necessity, the second of will. I do not command (sayth <hi>S. Paul</hi>) least I should burthen you; but <hi>I giue Counsayle,</hi> that I may allure you. Likewyse, concerning Pouerty, there is no commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: neither did our Lord say simply; <hi>sell all that thou hast;</hi> but, <hi>if thou vvilt be perfitt.</hi> If thou performest it, I will crowne thee; if thou doest
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:177048:76"/> not performe it, I will not punish thee. For those things, which are done by commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, receiue not such recompence: but those things, which are done freely, haue a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reward, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">THEODORE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (440.) in i. Cor. 7.25.</note>VVhen the Apostles sayd; <hi>if it be so, it is not good to marry:</hi> our Sauiour answered; <hi>all men receiue not this saying:</hi> and agayn: <hi>he that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, let him receiue it.</hi> For which cause, the diuine Apostle, <hi>S. Paul,</hi> sayeth; <hi>I haue no precept from our Lord, but I giue Counsayle.</hi> I bring no law, but I yeald my aduise, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Abbas (520.) doctr. 1. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed.</note>VVorthy, and illustrious men do not onely pay yerely tributes, but also they giue free gifts vnto their kinges. Likewyse our Fathers did not onely obserue the due precepts of God, but also they offered vnto him their voluntary gifts; as <hi>Virginity,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouerty</hi> For theis thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are gifts; because they are not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Our Lord sayed not vnto the Lawyer; <hi>sell all that thou hast,</hi> as commanding, but as counselling him. For that particular <hi>[if thou vvilt]</hi> is the speach of one that giueth Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle, and imposeth not a precept. VVherefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re our Fathers, with their other virtues, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto God <hi>Virginitie, Pouerty</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">MAXI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>VS Monachus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>0.) Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. de Charitate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>up. 67.</note>Those things which we do according to the will of God, are done partly vpon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and partly without, and, as I may
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:177048:76"/> say, by a voluntary oblation. As for example. To loue God, our neighbour, our enimy; not to committ adultery, not to kill &amp;c. theis things cannot be transgressed without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. But <hi>Virginitie, Pouerty</hi> &amp;c. belong not vnto the <hi>commandement;</hi> for they are in the nature of <hi>gifts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Christ prescribed not virginity vnto vs,<note place="margin">DAMASCEN. (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>30.) or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. fid. lib. 4. cap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as promulgating a law (for, according to his saying, <hi>all men receiue not this vvord</hi>) but he taught it vnto vs indeed, and hath giuen vs power to embrace it.</p>
               <p>The Apostle, speaking of virginitie,<note place="margin">OECVMEN (1070.) in 1. Cor. 7.</note> doth not deliuer <hi>a Precept,</hi> but giueth <hi>Counsayle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are many things,<note place="margin">THEOPHY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LACT (1071. vid. Baron. Tom. 11. anno Dom. 1071.) In cap. 1. ad Titum. v. 3.</note> which are not commāded, but are left vnto our free choyce; as <hi>Pouerty, Virginitie,</hi> &amp;c. For our Lord sayeth; he that can, let him receiue it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:177048:77"/>
            <head>An Aduertisement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I Desire thee (good Reader) to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that I freely offered vnto my aforesayd Iudges, and vnto other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in</hi> Oxford, <hi>and elswhere, to take their choyce of any of theis four reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable propositions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>FIRST.</hi> If I can not approoue, and iustify my Doctrine, by the vniforme consent of all Antiquity, successiuely from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, I vvill publickly abiure it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SECOND.</hi> If my Iudges can disprooue it by the verdict of any one Oxthodox vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that euer liued in the communion of holy Church, I vvill recant it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THIRD.</hi> Jf I can not prooue that their opinion is heresy, and condemned by the Church, J vvill intertayn it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FOVRTH.</hi> If any article of Religion, accepted by the Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> it self,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:177048:77"/> and established by vniforme consent, be plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely against my Doctrine, I vvill submitt my self vnto it, and yeald vnto this manner of triall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theis petitions, &amp; demands (though full of equity) could find no acceptance at my Iudges hands. Consider therefore the quality of theis men, &amp; the goodnes of their Religion: which hauing no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable grounds, sustayneth it self meerely by fraud, insolency, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:78"/>
            <head>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>incipall errours.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Reade.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>theis thinges.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">brought in the money</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ugning.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="6 letters">
                           <desc>••••••</desc>
                        </gap>dge.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>now I resolued.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>med it.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>at the sleepy.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>exacted.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41.</cell>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                     <cell>his.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>perceperunt.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>70.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>their</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>73.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>Charinthians.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>75.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>in deed:</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>extimescit.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>81.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>against</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>88.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>Scitis.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>praecisum.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>could not deny.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>129.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>I giue Counsayle.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>130.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>bade men.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>heard expedient.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>In the Margent.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Pag.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>Virgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ty.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>at.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31.</cell>
                     <cell>Monimum.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Timoth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>52.</cell>
                     <cell>nihilum.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>65.</cell>
                     <cell>originall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>93.</cell>
                     <cell>Cledon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>111.</cell>
                     <cell>by a Catholick.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pag. 132.</cell>
                     <cell>Dorotheus.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pag. 133.</cell>
                     <cell>Titum.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>It may please the courteous Reader to pardon theis, with some other, faults passed in the impression; and to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what difficulties we haue in vsing strangers herein.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177048:78"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>